<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abels offering. Or The earely, and most accepted sacrifice of a Christian Shewing how soone every soule is bounde to begin, &amp; betake himself, not only to the true, but also to the timely service of God. A sermon preached at Hamburg in November 1617. and now published at the instant entreaty of a godly Christian. By Iohn Wing (then) pastor to the English church, there.</title>
            <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855318</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855318</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20805</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20805)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1504:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abels offering. Or The earely, and most accepted sacrifice of a Christian Shewing how soone every soule is bounde to begin, &amp; betake himself, not only to the true, but also to the timely service of God. A sermon preached at Hamburg in November 1617. and now published at the instant entreaty of a godly Christian. By Iohn Wing (then) pastor to the English church, there.</title>
                  <author>Wing, John, of Flushing, Zealand.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 73, 70-71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Martin Abraham vander Nolck, dwelling at the signe of the Printing house,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Flushing :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; cropped.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20805:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20805:1"/>
            <p>ABELS OFFERING. OR THE EARELY, and moſt ACCEPTED Sacrifice of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Shewing how <hi>ſoone</hi> every ſoule is bounde to begin, &amp; betake himſelf, not only to the <hi>true,</hi> but alſo to the <hi>timely</hi> ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A SERMON</hi> Preached at <hi>Hamburg</hi> in November 1617, and now published at the inſtant entreaty of A <hi>Godly Christian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY IOHN WING <hi>(then)</hi> Paſtor to the English church, <hi>there,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea. 10.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>It is now time to ſeeke the Lord, till he rayne righteouſnes vpon you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT FLVSHING. <hi>Printed by</hi> Martin Abraham vander Nolck <hi>dwelling at the ſigne of the Printing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20805:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20805:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> THE OPHILVS, Lord <hi>Clinton,</hi> EARLE of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> And to the <hi>vertuous,</hi> and Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> BRIDGET his wife.</head>
            <head type="sub">AND TO The Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> WILLIAM, Lord <hi>Say,</hi> and <hi>Seale,</hi> with the <hi>Vertuous</hi> and Right <hi>Honorable,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> ELISABETH his wife.</head>
            <head type="sub">IOHN WING A poore vnworthy <hi>Minister</hi> of Ieſus Chriſt, wisheth all increaſe of all true <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>happines,</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight <hi>honorable Lords,</hi> and <hi>Ladyes,</hi> I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe it shall not be any way diſtaſtefull, or vnpleaſing to your <hi>honours,</hi> that a <hi>ſtranger</hi> is bolde to ſalute you, from <hi>beyonde the ſeas,</hi> and to publish your <hi>names,</hi> there, where your <hi>perſons</hi> may be as vnknowne to <hi>others;</hi> as <hi>myne</hi> is to your <hi>ſelves.</hi> I have not preſumed on this <hi>double dedication</hi> without all reaſon; for why? it is <hi>famouſly</hi> knowne, that you are the <hi>worthy</hi> examples of this ſubject, wherof I <hi>here</hi> treat. And I cannot but thinke, that they are the <hi>fitteſt Patrones</hi> of divine bookes, whome God hath made, the <hi>faithfull Patternes</hi> of the doctrine contayned in them. It is <hi>long</hi> ſince I have heard of your <hi>early,</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> proceedings in piety. Having <hi>now</hi> this opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, I could not <hi>longer</hi> contayne in ſilence, but reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="tcp:20805:3"/>to place you in the <hi>beginning</hi> of this litle booke, that they which reade, ſeeing ſuch <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>noble</hi> preſidents, of the practiſe <hi>herein</hi> preſſed, might have the more <hi>powerfull jnducements,</hi> to draw them, to doe the ſame. The <hi>Lord</hi> of heaven, keepe you <hi>all,</hi> in your moſt <hi>holy</hi> courſe, &amp; bring you to the <hi>end</hi> of this happy <hi>race,</hi> that every of <hi>you</hi> may, (after all <hi>honorable falici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes</hi> enjoyed on earth) poſeſſe thoſe <hi>infinite,</hi> and endles glories, prepared, for all that love his name, in whome I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>FLVSHING. <date>the 30. of October 1621.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours <hi>Honours</hi> in all ſervice, for the <hi>honour</hi> of God. IOHN WING. <hi>Pastor</hi> to the <hi>English</hi> church, at <hi>Flushing</hi> in ZEELANT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <list>
               <item>Pag. 18. lin. 23. put in, <hi>and gaue</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pag, 43. lin. 33. put out <hi>he</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pag. 49. lin. 24. for <hi>albe,</hi> read <hi>able</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20805:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ABELS OFFERING,</hi> OR THE Earely, and moſt acceptable ſacrifice of a Chriſtian.</head>
            <head type="sub">Shewing how <hi>ſoone,</hi> every ſoule is bounde to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to betake himſelf, not only to the <hi>true,</hi> but alſo, to the <hi>timely</hi> ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Gen. 4.4.</bibl>
                  <p>And Abel, he alſo brought of the firſtlings of his flock, and the fatt therof.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE three former chapters of this holy Hiſtory being ſpent in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the <hi>worldes creation,</hi> and of the moſt wonderfull and glorious workemanship of God, as in every other creature, ſoe eſpecially in <hi>Man,</hi> whoſe happy eſtate while he <hi>stood,</hi> and miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition when he <hi>fell,</hi> and moſt gracious <hi>recovery</hi> from his fall, with divers other <hi>divine</hi> occurrents (next and jmmediately following) being at large related vnto vs. It now pleaſeth the <hi>holy Ghost</hi> to goe further in this ſacred narration, and in the beginning of this <hi>fourth</hi> chapter, to acquaint vs with the <hi>multiplication</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20805:4"/>of man-kinde. And here we have the ſtory of the <hi>firſt two,</hi> that were ever borne into the world, to wit, the two firſt <hi>ſons,</hi> of their, and our <hi>first</hi> parents, (I diſpute not whether they were <hi>twinnes,</hi> the text ſeemeth to contradict it, though ſome doe <hi>weakely</hi> conceit it, neither doth it carry, or conclude any materiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, whether they were or noe) concerning whome, we have a <hi>threefolde</hi> deſcription.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. of their <hi>birth,</hi> and naturall being. ver. 1.2.</item>
               <item>2. of their <hi>buſines,</hi> and civill being: ver. 2.</item>
               <item>3. of their <hi>religion,</hi> and ſpirituall condition. ver. 3.4.</item>
            </list>
            <p>They were both <hi>borne</hi> into the world of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: by them alſo were they both <hi>employed</hi> in the world; and theſe <hi>two</hi> are only named or mentioned without any further diſcourſe: But the <hi>third</hi> thing, to wit, that which concerneth the matter of <hi>religion,</hi> is that which the Lord doth intend to treat off, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt vpon. In the world, and affaires of the earth, men may lawfully be of <hi>divers</hi> profeſſions, trades, &amp; occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations and it is needfull they should be ſoe. But in <hi>religion</hi> it cannot be thus; piety cannot admitt a <hi>diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> the bleſſed worship of God will beare no <hi>variety</hi> at all, it muſt be <hi>vniforme,</hi> as that <hi>one</hi> God is, who is worshipped. And ſoe was this of theſe two brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, ſo farre as the ſame appeared <hi>viſiblely</hi> to men, in the externall act of ſacrificing, which practiſe they had <hi>(doubtles)</hi> learned of their parents, who were (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout queſtion) taught of God how to excerciſe this duty, though the <hi>letter of the ſcripture</hi> be ſilent in both as it is in divers other excellent <hi>truthes,</hi> which yet we ſtand bound to acknowledg, by vertue of ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and vndeniable conſequence as doth clearely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20805:4"/>conclude the ſame, without <hi>litterall</hi> teſtimony in any expreſſe tearmes to avouch it.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the ſacrifice of the ſons of <hi>Adam, Cain,</hi> and <hi>Abell,</hi> there is a double difference noted.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. of the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> they offred.</item>
               <item>2. of the <hi>effect</hi> they found with God, to who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me they were offred.</item>
            </list>
            <p>That which is obſervable in their ſacrifices, is this, that wheras <hi>Cain,</hi> careleſly and without choiſe offred <hi>[of the fruit of the grounde]</hi> not regarding <hi>what</hi> he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, ſoe he brought <hi>ſome what,</hi> contrary to the law of thoſe offrings, which required the <hi>first</hi> of all fruits: It is reported of <hi>Abell,</hi> &amp; commended in him, that he was very regard-full and reſpective, to ſacrifice to his God, of the <hi>firſt</hi> of his flock, and among the <hi>first,</hi> the <hi>best</hi> he could pick and chuſe.</p>
            <p>And according to the difference of theſe <hi>acts,</hi> the <hi>effect</hi> was alſo different with the Lord, who ſeemeth to ſuite and fit, his <hi>justice</hi> to <hi>Cain,</hi> that as he had <hi>no reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect</hi> what <hi>offering</hi> he brought, ſoe had God <hi>no reſpect</hi> to him, or that he <hi>offered;</hi> and his <hi>favour</hi> to <hi>Abell,</hi> vnto whoſe perſon and ſacrifice, the Lord had gracious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, as he was moſt heedefull to preſent the <hi>choyſe,</hi> and <hi>cheife,</hi> of all he had to the Lord.</p>
            <p>And in this particuler doth <hi>Moſes,</hi> the man of God, and pen-man of this part of Gods word, inſiſt, &amp; ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much of the things that iſſued herevpon, both on <hi>Ahells</hi> part, and <hi>Cains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here (it may be) ſome will move a queſtion, how <hi>Moſes</hi> who was borne many <hi>hundred,</hi> and ſome <hi>thouſands</hi> of yeares after the creation, could come to know theſe things, and to ſet them downe in ſuch <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act</hi> order vnto vs.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20805:5"/>
            <p>To <hi>moue</hi> this queſtion, is to <hi>make</hi> queſtion of Gods truth, and to bring into doubt, all that he hath recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this whole booke of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and all ſuch other things as fell out before his birth and ripe yeares, in <hi>Exodus;</hi> for in his <hi>infancy</hi> we cannot conceive him to be any way one of Gods principall ſecretaryes, or meete to be entruſted with this rare jmployment of penning any part of ſcripture, eſpecially conſidering that he was brought vp in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> court as a <hi>Pagan,</hi> for the firſt <hi>forty</hi> yeares of his life.</p>
            <p>But for the cleare manifeſtation of this matter, and for the juſtification of the <hi>authority</hi> of this ſacred boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke againſt all accurſed <hi>cavills;</hi> we anſwer and doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that howſoever every thing reported therein by <hi>Moſes</hi> were acted long before his birth, yet nevertheleſſe all things written therin, are as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely true, as if <hi>Moſes</hi> had beene borne, &amp; had ſeene, and heard, each paſſage in his owne perſon. The Lord made choyſe of a man living ſo long after theſe things were done, that he might honour himſelf, and this his <hi>ſacred</hi> hiſtorie aboue all humane, hiſtories vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>For wheras no profane writer is able <hi>infaillibly</hi> to report any thing (for matter of fact) but what was done in his owne dayes, and came to paſſe in his owne ceartayne knowledge; the Lord is able to inſtruct, ſuch as he will ſet a worke to report the proceedings of his churches in all ages, in the <hi>incontroleable</hi> truth of all things that came to paſſe, though they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde it, were vnborne when they were acted. And who knoweth whether the Lord hath not done this; and of purpoſe made vſe of ſuch perſons who had not a <hi>being</hi> in the world, till long after the time wherin the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20805:5"/>things themſelves which they relate had their <hi>being,</hi> that ſoe he might shew himſelf an <hi>alſufficient</hi> inſtructor of his ſervants in thoſe things which were done long <hi>before</hi> their time, and declared long <hi>after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not my purpoſe to digreſſe into any <hi>generall</hi> diſcourſe of thoſe evidences that doe authoriſe, and warrant the <hi>whole</hi> ſcripture, which are diſcovered at large by many worthy, judicious, and learned <hi>Divines</hi> only, that it may manifeſtly appeare that this booke is no leſſe ſcripture then any other, let vs take into our harts the due conſideration of thoſe things which may as <hi>vnreproveably</hi> argue God to be the <hi>author,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> to be the <hi>penner</hi> of the ſame, and they are (among a multitude that might be produced) theſe few that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes</hi> doth tell vs of ſome paſſages concerning God <hi>before</hi> the creation, which no creature could heare, or vnderſtand as that of the firſt creature, &amp; all the reſt, when he ſayd of every of them: <hi>[Let there be light, &amp;c.]</hi> who could tell what God ſpake touching every of theſe, ſeing as yet they <hi>were</hi> not, &amp; when they <hi>were,</hi> yet till <hi>man</hi> was created all other were voyd of vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hee relates to vs touching the creation of <hi>man,</hi> what God ſayd of his making to wit, the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>forme</hi> of his body, and the <hi>infuſion</hi> of his ſoule, as alſo of the manner of the making of the <hi>woman</hi> when the man was in a deepe ſleepe, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it not, and what the man ſayd of the woman, when the Lord brought her to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After the creation, he report's the paſſages of mans <hi>fall,</hi> and diſcover's the ſubtiltyes of <hi>Satan,</hi> in ſeducing the firſt man and the firſt woman, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20805:6"/>relations muſt needes be of God, for we cannot conceit that the <hi>divell</hi> would ſoe detect himſelf, in the evill both of his <hi>groſſe</hi> ſin, and <hi>great</hi> punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="4">4. After mans fall, he tell's vs of divers ſecret paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as of <hi>Adams</hi> knowing his wife: of <hi>Cains</hi> anger conceived inwardly, and vnjuſtly, againſt <hi>Abel</hi> his brother, before it brake out: of <hi>Noahs</hi> druncke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and nakednes: of <hi>Lots</hi> fayling, and the manner therof, how he was abuſed by his <hi>daughters,</hi> with their cloſe carriage of the matter, &amp; how he knew not what was done, when he had ſlept with them <hi>both:</hi> of the cloſe conveyance which <hi>Rebecca</hi> vſed to obtayne the bleſſing for <hi>Iacob,</hi> with the moſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate circumſtances therof: and a multitude more of the like to theſe things, ſoe <hi>ſecret,</hi> that no flesh could know, or relate, but they muſt needes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by the Lord himſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He make's narration of the <hi>ſins,</hi> of the moſt <hi>holy</hi> men and women, either, <hi>that</hi> which was <hi>common</hi> in thoſe times to moſt of them, as the <hi>Polygamie</hi> of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> or ſuch offences as any <hi>one</hi> of them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly fell into, not ſparing <hi>Abraham</hi> the freind of God, nor any of the <hi>ſincerest</hi> of his ſervants, which a good man would have done, had he beene guided but by his owne ſpirit. Nay, (which doth abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely ſeale the truth and authority of his writings to be of God) <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpare's not <hi>himſelf</hi> in his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſins, but make's a manifeſt diſcovery of his owne <hi>infidelity,</hi> and vnadviſed <hi>anger,</hi> and the juſt punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God vpon him for them both. This <hi>impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality,</hi> argue's a ſupernaturall ſpirit to guide it: when a man cannot ſpare his freind, nor himſelf but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20805:6"/>will leave both, vpon everlaſting record to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and blemished to all poſterity. A thing not vſuall <hi>(if at all vſed)</hi> in humane hiſtory, wherin men ſpeake, and write the beſt they <hi>can</hi> (and many times <hi>more then they should</hi>) of themſelves, &amp; thoſe whome they favour. It muſt be God that muſt make men thus to doe: &amp; therefore this is one of the <hi>prerogatives royall</hi> of his writings.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And laſtly, he tell's vs of the <hi>most ſecret things</hi> that can be imagined; nothing can be conceived ſoe cloſe as the <hi>counſell of heaven:</hi> what God ſpeaketh there, who can heare? eſpecially when he ſpeaketh not in any ſuch ſort, or ſoe openly where Angell's may heare, but in his owne private <hi>cloſet,</hi> nay (which is yet more) in his owne breaſt or <hi>boſome:</hi> yet <hi>Moſes</hi> can tell the world, not only what God ſayd in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> but what he ſayd in his <hi>hart,</hi> &amp; how he was jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly affected. Soe we finde in <hi>one</hi> chapter of this booke, where <hi>Moſes</hi> make's knowne how God <hi>[repented, and was greived at his hart, at mans wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:]</hi> and in <hi>another,</hi> how he was graciouſly diſpoſed for the continnance of the conſtant courſe and ſucceſſion of all the affaires of this inferiour world ſaying <hi>[And the Lord ſayd in his hart, I will not againe curſe the earth &amp;c.]</hi> See, <hi>Moſes</hi> is privy to Gods <hi>hart,</hi> and can make vs know, what were his moſt <hi>jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde</hi> reſolutions. And who could give him the leaſt light, or acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theſe things but God himſelf, who made him his <hi>ſecretary,</hi> and ſo made theſe <hi>ſecrets</hi> knowne to him.</p>
            <p>And thus by all theſe <hi>evidences,</hi> (which are <hi>common</hi> to all other ſcripture as well as this, but <hi>coummunicable</hi> to no bookes but the booke of God) we ſee that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20805:7"/>is no reaſon of doubting or debateing any thing in this parte of holy writ, (or any parcell of it) becauſe it was penned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and he borne ſo long after all things written and recorded in the ſame, were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and paſt. He had a ſinguler and all ſufficient <hi>tutor,</hi> even the moſt wiſe God, and he himſelf did <hi>endite,</hi> all that he taught and enabled <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>write,</hi> ſo that every jot and tittle of this booke of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> muſt be of abſolute and infaillible truth.</p>
            <p>And ſoe having now (by the way) cleared this ſcruple, we should proceede vnto our diſcovery of <hi>Abels</hi> ſacrifice, as we have it here layd downe, in the words of the text which make report vnto vs <hi>what kinde</hi> of ſacrifice it was, and <hi>wherof</hi> it conſiſted. But we muſt <hi>(first)</hi> take away another doubt, which may be made by ſome, how <hi>Abell</hi> could know the <hi>minde</hi> of God for <hi>theſe matters,</hi> and ſoe readily offer a ſacrifice of this kinde, and doe it ſoe ſuitably to Gods <hi>preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> conſidering, that as yet the <hi>law</hi> of the offering of firſt fruits, nor any other part of the <hi>morall,</hi> or <hi>ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall</hi> was not given. We anſwer, it was <hi>giuen,</hi> but not <hi>written,</hi> as we have it <hi>now,</hi> it was given in thoſe dayes by divine <hi>tradition; originaly</hi> from God to man, and <hi>ſucceſſively</hi> from man to man.</p>
            <p>Then did the <hi>father</hi> informe the <hi>childe,</hi> &amp; acquaint him with the dutyes that pertayned to piety, and the <hi>children</hi> they received it from their <hi>parents,</hi> &amp; obeyed it as from God.</p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> courſe and manner of revealing the will of God by <hi>this kinde</hi> of traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, endured all the dayes of the holy <hi>Patriarches,</hi> and ſuch as lived after them, till <hi>Moſes,</hi> and alſo during all the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> till that part of his life, wherin the Lord employd him
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20805:7"/>about the penning of this booke, and that is <hi>diverſly</hi> conjectured of; <hi>ſome</hi> ſuppoſe it to be written <hi>before</hi> he went into <hi>Egypt</hi> within the compaſſe of theſe four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares wherin he kept sheepe in <hi>Madian; others</hi> imagine he did it immediately after his departing out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> even in the firſt yeare therof. Howbeit this, (as the former) is no point of ſuch importance, as that we muſt of neceſſity have an exact knowledge of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But that Gods law was delivered by this kinde of <hi>tradition,</hi> till the time we ſpeake off, we nothing doubt, and therefore the more foule is that ſlander layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs by the <hi>papiſt,</hi> that we acknowledg not, nor endure any <hi>traditions;</hi> judeede thoſe that are <hi>popish</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written,</hi> we cannot abide, but doe abhorre them all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>none</hi> of them can be defended but by <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> of them (in particular) are apparantly <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</hi> But that there were traditions <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce,</hi> to wit, ſuch as the Lord by <hi>himſelf,</hi> or by his <hi>Angells,</hi> made know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to <hi>man;</hi> &amp; man beleeved &amp; related to his poſterity, we doe no more deny, then we doe that <hi>Moſes</hi> penned this part of holy ſcripture, which (till his time) was a <hi>tradition</hi> and <hi>vnwritten,</hi> but can be <hi>none</hi> from that time forward. And if the Lord have ceaſed his <hi>owne,</hi> hath any man power to erect <hi>more,</hi> that are none of <hi>his?</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially now that his holy will is <hi>ſufficiently</hi> revealed, in the writings of the <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> That there <hi>were ſome</hi> traditions we freely confeſſe; that any <hi>are</hi> (of God) now we dirictly deny; thoſe that <hi>are</hi> (being not of God) we deteſt, becauſe they are the fruit of the <hi>Popes</hi> braine, <hi>who</hi> hath a very <hi>crazy head</hi> in heavenly things, though he be applauded to be the <hi>head</hi> of the church, and able to diſtill <hi>ſpirituall</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20805:8"/>influence into it.</p>
            <p>But to returne to <hi>Abel,</hi> it is probable, that he received the light and knowledge he had to offer ſacrifice, from his father, who from God did inſtruct him how, and what to doe, in ſuch duties as were to be required of him. And vpon <hi>this</hi> did he embrace, and obey the Lord in his ordinances; which courſe of <hi>his,</hi> and his <hi>forwardnes</hi> thus to doe, in thoſe <hi>times</hi> wherin no ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was <hi>penned,</hi> nor every man that ſpake of the things of God <hi>traditionally,</hi> ſo infalliblely inſpired, as were <hi>all</hi> they, by whome the Lord hath left his truth <hi>written</hi> to vs, shall riſe vp againſt vs, to condemne our <hi>vntowardnes,</hi> who refuſe to be <hi>taught</hi> of God, and to be obedient to him, though he hath left vs a more happy way to <hi>learne,</hi> then they had, who had but <hi>a part</hi> of his good pleaſure manifeſted, and that <hi>not written,</hi> wheras we have the <hi>whole,</hi> and <hi>written,</hi> vpon ſuch records as can never be razed. The <hi>ſaints,</hi> of thoſe <hi>times,</hi> were moſt willing to take knowledge of the wayes of God and yeeld their obedience to them, by that meanes (which in compariſon of <hi>ours</hi>) are but <hi>meane,</hi> and were but <hi>weake,</hi> (yet enough to bring them to God, who lived by faith in the truth <hi>thus</hi> revealed). The <hi>ſinners</hi> of our dayes, to whome the Lord hath diſpenced a <hi>more</hi> abſolute, and <hi>moſt</hi> ſufficient courſe, of comming neere to him, are farre from the Lord, and will not give him, neither <hi>ſuch,</hi> nor ſoe <hi>much</hi> duty, as theſe did, whoſe knowledg and practiſe is not ſoe much <hi>magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed,</hi> as ours shalbe manifeſted &amp; <hi>plagued</hi> of the Lord, who looke's <hi>they</hi> should be the <hi>best</hi> ſchollers, who have the <hi>best</hi> teaching.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> Miſerable will it be with thoſe men to whome the Lord shall ſay; <hi>theſe</hi> knew litle of my minde (in reſpect of <hi>you</hi>) yet have done much; I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20805:8"/>made it all knowne to you, yet have you done litle or nothing.</p>
            <p>Let not this conſideration be in vaine, but thinke we, how <hi>cheerefully Abel</hi> learned, &amp; how <hi>conſcionably</hi> he performed, the worship of his God, having but <hi>litle helpe</hi> to further him: that we by due ponderation he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rof, may be both <hi>ashamed</hi> for our faylings paſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force our ſelves, (as it were) by a <hi>holy violence</hi> for time to come, to be more faithfull and induſtrious, both to <hi>know,</hi> and to <hi>doe,</hi> what on our part, we owe vnto the Lord, what vnſepakeable shame is it? that we should lye <hi>behinde</hi> them, that have gone <hi>before</hi> vs in thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, wherin <hi>many</hi> of them, had but <hi>few</hi> to follow, nor any ſcripture to learne them: but we have both Gods <hi>whole</hi> booke to <hi>giude</hi> vs, and all his bleſſed ſaints are gone before vs, yet are we exceeding short of thoſe holy ones who lived graciouſly in that age which may truly be called the <hi>infancy</hi> both of the <hi>world,</hi> and of the <hi>church;</hi> But I will not dwell here, we ſee the holy Ghoſte beare's record of <hi>Abels</hi> offering: let vs now come to the words of the text which tell vs what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſacrifice it was. And <hi>Abel, he alſo brought of the [firstlings] or, first borne [of his flock,
<note place="margin">Exod. 22.29.30. cap. 34.19 26. Levit. 23.10.12. Num. 15.20.21. Deut. 12.17. cap. 18.4. cap. 26.1.2.11.</note> and of the fate of them.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the <hi>first-lings,</hi> or, <hi>firſt borne</hi>] that is, the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of cattell that the Lord gave him; The Lord made a moſt <hi>exact law</hi> for the offeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the <hi>firſt</hi> borne, both of man, and beaſt, and of all fruits vnto him, and this law of his we finde to be very frequently repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in divers places of the foure bookes of <hi>Moſes Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Leviticus Numbers,</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomie.</hi> And as it was often itterated by God to <hi>Jſraell,</hi> ſoe was it faithfully obeyed by <hi>Iſraell</hi> before the Lord, both <hi>before</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20805:9"/>the captivity in <hi>Hezekiah</hi> dayes;
<note place="margin">2. Chron. 31.1.51. Neh. 10.3.32.35.</note> and <hi>after,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> as appeareth in the ſtorie of their lives: nay, from the begining, before this law was given (in writing) <hi>Abel</hi> (you ſee) is carefull to bring his <hi>firſt,</hi> and I nothing doubt, but <hi>Adam</hi> his father did it <hi>before</hi> him, as we noted before.</p>
            <p>But here it way be enquired wherefore theſe things were offred, in <hi>thoſe</hi> times, and among all the <hi>Jewes</hi> to the time of Chriſt, and are not <hi>ſoe</hi> now among <hi>vs,</hi> we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they proper to their worship?</p>
            <p>We anſwer, they were ſoe as the <hi>Iewish</hi> people were a people <hi>peculiar</hi> to God, and he taught them his min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de after ſuch a manner, as never <hi>any nation</hi> but they had it, to wit, by shaddowes, types and ceremonies, ſuch as were to endure for a ſeaſon, and to dye when once <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> the Lord of life did appeare, and had fulfilled this law of <hi>Iewish rites,</hi> which perished and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came fruſtrate (in Gods purpoſe) aſſoone as, <hi>his [con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummatum est]</hi> was out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>But if theſe <hi>Moſacaill</hi> rites were <hi>shaddowes,</hi> what was the <hi>ſubstance?</hi> what was the truth and ſignification of theſe types, and ceremonyes, and of theſe <hi>firſt</hi> frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and <hi>first</hi> borne, in particuler?</p>
            <p>We anſwer;
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.1</note> all men muſt know that the whole ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall law was a type, or shaddow, the <hi>apoctle</hi> tells vs ſoe, &amp; (in the generall) every ceremonie therein did <hi>ſome way</hi> reſpect Chriſt, who is the end of <hi>this law</hi> &amp; hath abolished the ſame; one way or other, Chriſt was aymed at in <hi>each</hi> offering. Now for the matter meant and ſignifyed by theſe <hi>first fruits,</hi> and <hi>first borne</hi> they alſo had their reference to the Lord Ieſus, who is entituled,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> both <hi>[the first fruits of them that ſleepe]</hi> and, <hi>[the firſt borne of every creature.</hi> Yet not to him <hi>only,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20805:9"/>(though <hi>principally)</hi> had they their <hi>totall</hi> relation, as if nothing elſe at all, were to be shaddowed by theſe things, but, as to <hi>him</hi> (to wit, to Chriſt) they were <hi>strictly,</hi> and <hi>properly</hi> aſſigned, ſoe, in a <hi>larger ſence</hi> and <hi>vſe,</hi> the perpetuall morality of this law was, that our choyſeſt, and cheife, our firſt, and beſt, the prime and principall, (not of our <hi>fruits,</hi> or of our <hi>beast,</hi> but) of our <hi>lives,</hi> of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> should be given to the ſervice of our God. That aſſoone as he pleaſeth to enlarge and encreaſe the <hi>abilityes</hi> of our bodyes, and <hi>facultyes</hi> of our ſoules, that we can once diſcerne betweene good and evill, and are able to put a difference betweene theſe in our opinion, and practiſe, we should <hi>inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently,</hi> and forth-with betake our ſelves to worship and obey the Lord, and from that time proceede in the ſame, during all our dayes.</p>
            <p>But it is further noted here, in the text, that <hi>Abells</hi> ſacrifice was <hi>[Of the fatt of his flock.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fatt</hi> in ſcriptures hath divers <hi>references,</hi> and <hi>(accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly</hi>) divers <hi>ſences,</hi> as the nature of things to which it is referred doth require. It retayneth his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſignification, when it is referred to <hi>naturall</hi> things: we read of <hi>Fatneſſe</hi> attributed to the <hi>earth;</hi> to <hi>oyle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 27.28. cap. 45.18</note> to <hi>wine;</hi> the <hi>beſt</hi> of which, God doth call the <hi>fattest,</hi> and the fatteſt of any thing is the <hi>best,</hi> as the fatteſt land, the <hi>beſt</hi> land; and ſoe of the reſt. And ſoe we account the <hi>fatteſt</hi> beaſt, the <hi>beſt,</hi> (eſpecially being young too,) as theſe firſt-borne were.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>fattnes</hi> is affirmed of things <hi>ſpirituall</hi> (or things naturall, conſidered ſpiritually) it carieth contrary ſences, and ſignifies both the <hi>best,</hi> and the <hi>worst.</hi> For we finde <hi>David</hi> where he would shew a moſt ſinfull hart, to ſay, it is a <hi>[hart as fat as brawne,]</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20805:10"/>and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.20. Iſ. 6. Mat. 23.14.15. Pſal. 36.2. Pſal 92.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> and <hi>Christ</hi> after him, when they ſpeake of a hart given over of God, ſay thus <hi>[make the hart of this people fatt.]</hi> On the other ſide, the moſt abundant and <hi>best bleſsings</hi> pertayning to the ſolacing of the ſaints, are called <hi>[the fatnes of thy houſe:]</hi> and thoſe godly and <hi>well-growne</hi> chriſtians, who have eaten, and fed freely, of thoſe <hi>divine delicates,</hi> and by the benefit of them are come to ſome good meaſure of ability, in good things, are ſayd to be <hi>[fatt and flourishing.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But with this <hi>myſticall</hi> ſence, or vſe of the word we meddle not, in our text it is taken moſt <hi>properly,</hi> for fat beaſts, <hi>[the fat of his flock]</hi> that is the <hi>beſt</hi> there. So that the <hi>ſumme</hi> of all that is ſayd here of <hi>Abells</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring is <hi>this:</hi> that <hi>he</hi> being made partaker of true grace and guided by God to shew it in the fruits therof, doth by faith offer vnto God ſuch a ſacrifice as was <hi>now</hi> required, namely, the firſt, &amp; (among all the firſt) the <hi>very beſt</hi> of the <hi>flock</hi> he did attend.</p>
            <p>I ſay <hi>now</hi> required, for <hi>after-ward</hi> God commanded and expected <hi>more,</hi> but as yet there was <hi>no</hi> temple, or tabernacle, <hi>no</hi> high preiſt, <hi>nor</hi> any Levite, <hi>no</hi> fire from heaven, (at leaſt) that burnt continually, nor many other things, which came in, in ſucceeding times: <hi>ſome</hi> when the <hi>Arke</hi> and tabernacle was erected, <hi>more,</hi> when the <hi>Temple</hi> was builded, and all other things ſet in order, according to Gods preſcription touching each particuler.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> Howbeit <hi>Abel</hi> (in the meane time) doth his beſt, and offers to his vtmoſt power, what <hi>his</hi> preſent <hi>ſtate,</hi> and the preſent <hi>time</hi> may permit, shewing therby that <hi>true</hi> grace will doe what it <hi>can,</hi> though it cannot doe <hi>all</hi> it would, or should, in the ſeruice of God;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20805:10"/>others may doe <hi>more,</hi> in times &amp; places which afforde more meanes, but ſincerity will shew it ſelf in the <hi>moſt</hi> that may be done for the time being; though we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy but litle meanes, or few helpes to further vs, yet a ſounde hart will make ſome honeſt <hi>shift,</hi> to doe ſomething that may be pleaſing to God.</p>
            <p>This is worth noteing (by the way) becauſe it mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te's <hi>fitly,</hi> with their fearefull jmpiety, who let all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and piety <hi>alone,</hi> becauſe they cannot doe <hi>all:</hi> like to miſerable and deſperate <hi>bankrupts,</hi> who becauſe they are not able to give every man <hi>all,</hi> will pay not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing <hi>at all</hi> to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; which deceit who could endure? Nay, learne to doe better of good <hi>Abell</hi> (and all Gods ſaints who lived in the firſt times) doe ſomething the <hi>moſt</hi> and <hi>beſt,</hi> thou canſt, and the Lord will accept thee according to the <hi>willing</hi> minde thou haſt, to goe as farre as <hi>weake</hi> meanes will further thee. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> A man doth not more manifeſt <hi>weake grace,</hi> in not doing Gods worke <hi>compleatly,</hi> then he doth evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <hi>true gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> in doing what he is able to doe, <hi>conſcionably.</hi> The Lord regarde's men according to <hi>his</hi> meanes, and <hi>their</hi> mindes, in his ſervice. They that offred vprightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>preisthood</hi> was ordered, were as acceptable to God, and <hi>ſome</hi> of them had as <hi>much,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> of them had as <hi>true</hi> grace, as any that ſacrificed after. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> A <hi>wiſe</hi> chriſtian, may employ <hi>much</hi> grace, vpon <hi>litle</hi> meanes, and (I thinke) the <hi>least</hi> meanes that ever the Lord doth give, may exerciſe the <hi>most</hi> grace the beſt of vs have, if we play the <hi>good husbands,</hi> &amp; ſet it well a work. But this is by the way, let vs now make toward the <hi>mayne</hi> thing,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4</note> we meane to handle in this offring of <hi>Abel,</hi> which is ſoe commended in him, both here &amp; in other places of ſcripture.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20805:11"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctri∣ne. </seg>
               </label> And that is, <hi>that morall</hi> of this practiſe <hi>ceremoniall,</hi> which concerneth vs chriſtians, to wit, <hi>That it is the vndeniable duty of every one, to giue vnto God the glory of his first abilityes, both of ſoule &amp; body, &amp; to bestow their first powers in the ſeruice of his maieſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This leſſon <hi>Abell</hi> needed not to have learned of the <hi>firſt</hi> borne of his beaſts, had not his father <hi>Adam</hi> fallen, and deprived him (and <hi>vs</hi> all,) of thoſe <hi>firſt</hi> &amp; <hi>beſt</hi> fruits of created grace, which the Lord gave him, when <hi>he</hi> filled him the <hi>firſt</hi> day of his life, with the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> of all knowledge, holynes, and righteouſnes, and made him as holy, and as happy, as a creature might be on this earth. Had not theſe <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of this grace perished in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſoe, as that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver man but he might taſte them, they would have taught vs what to doe aſſoone as we could have done any thing, <hi>that grace</hi> &amp;c, would quickly have carried vs to the fountaine of <hi>grace,</hi> from whence, as it came but <hi>lately,</hi> it would have returned <hi>naturally,</hi> as the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers into the ſea. For Adams graces were as <hi>naturall,</hi> as his breath, it was all one to him, to doe any duty to God, and to himſelf, both were <hi>alike eaſy</hi> vnto him.</p>
            <p>But now the caſe is altred, it is nothing ſoe, but cleane contrary altogether, his firſt <hi>beſt</hi> leſſon muſt be taught <hi>Abel</hi> (yea and Adam too) by his firſt <hi>beſt</hi> beaſt which he muſt now give to that God to whome he should have given <hi>himſelf</hi> from his <hi>first</hi> being, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſt muſt be ſacrifiſed to <hi>shame</hi> him, who being <hi>once</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gods, hath <hi>now</hi> made himſelf worſe then the beaſt that perisheth, <hi>now</hi> muſt man have <hi>dumbe</hi> ſchoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that cannot ſpeake, and <hi>vnreaſonable</hi> yea <hi>ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi> alſo, which cannot vnderſtand or heare his ſpeech, and ſomewhat muſt be done to them, aſſoone as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20805:11"/>they are in the world, to shew man, what <hi>we</hi> once <hi>(when time was)</hi> could have done, and what for ever he ought to doe, from the time of his owne firſt being. The <hi>first</hi> of our flock, the <hi>firſt</hi> of our fruit, muſt teach vs to whome the <hi>firſt</hi> of our ſelves, doth of right apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: even to the Lord, to whome a <hi>beaſt</hi> muſt be give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceremonially, in ſtead of a <hi>man</hi> morally. And this being <hi>one</hi> morall and meaning of this ceremonie, it moſt needes be our duty thus to doe. Even this <hi>shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> shewe's vs, that as a <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and a <hi>shaddow,</hi> doe from the firſt inſtant goe together <hi>inſeparably,</hi> and for ever; ſoe should we ha ve beene to our God, ever from our beginning to have followed him whereſoever he had gone before vs, and to have cleaved continually to him, in the obedience we owe him all the dayes of our life, both firſt and laſt.</p>
            <p>And this truth of God of the <hi>early</hi> offering of our ſelves vnto the Lord, is not only typed out and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied here, by theſe <hi>firſt</hi> beaſtes, and fruits, that muſt be ſacrificed; but it is ſubſtantially confirmed in other ſcriptures, wherein the Lord doth more <hi>expreſly,</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his minde in this matter.</p>
            <p>I will not, (for I neede not) heape vp many evidences; let vs conſider only, to what end it may be (if this be not Gods truth,) that the Lord doth ſoe often call vpon parents, touching their duty to their children on this behalfe, to nurture, to tutor, &amp; inſtruct them, in all holy informations, even in their <hi>childe-hood, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age</hi> and <hi>minerity,</hi> ſo ſoone as they can be diſcerned to be capable and vnderſtanding in any thing. <hi>[Teach a childe]</hi> ſaith <hi>Salom on. [Fathers, bring vp your children in the feare and information of the Lord]</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> with moe that might be added. In any of which, <hi>dare</hi> any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20805:12"/>man jmagine that the Lord calls for any thing more then <hi>his due,</hi> and if he doe not, then doth the duty of our <hi>first dayes</hi> belong to the Lord, our <hi>first</hi> powers, &amp; abilities, are his in all right, and he muſt have our <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> ſoe ſoone as we can doe <hi>any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, why are many commended in ſcripture for being carefull herin, and their examples recorded for our <hi>jmitation?</hi> is it not becauſe we should trace them in this truth which ſome of them have learned, <hi>more</hi> then we, with much <hi>leſſe</hi> teaching then we have? For inſtance,
<note place="margin">Joſh. 24.2.13. Gen. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> who in his owne <hi>first times,</hi> was tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in jdolatry with <hi>Terah</hi> his father, and ſoe he gave not the <hi>firſt</hi> fruits of his owne life, yet for his poſterity, God prefumeth on his fidelity this way, and ſaith, he knew his minde ſoe well for this matter, that he was fure <hi>[he would teach his children and command them]</hi> in the things of God, and therevpon acquaints him with his ſecret purpoſe concerning <hi>Sodome.</hi> We ſee <hi>Abraham</hi> did know this our <hi>doctrine</hi> to be his duty, yet he had neither his <hi>fathers</hi> example, nor his <hi>owne</hi> practiſe in his <hi>firſt</hi> yeares, nor <hi>Salomon,</hi> nor <hi>Paul,</hi> to call vpon him but the Lord <hi>himſelf</hi> taught him this truth, him a hart to doe it.</p>
            <p>And have you not alſo read what is recorded of <hi>Hannah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sam. 1.</note> the happy mother of <hi>Samuell,</hi> and what her reſolution was, when she went to pray for a childe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore she had ever a one, namely this, to give him to God, and that ſoe, as the Lord might have the <hi>first</hi> fruits of him, even <hi>[from the day of his birth to the day of his death,]</hi> and when the Lord ſaw her ſoe well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, he quickly graunted what she deſired.</p>
            <p>It were as eaſy to inſtance many <hi>moe,</hi> as theſe <hi>two,</hi> who have hearkened to God herin, &amp; honoured him with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20805:12"/>the firſt of theſe <hi>fruits of their body</hi> which he had given them, as of olde <hi>theſe</hi> did with the <hi>fruits</hi> of their <hi>beasts.</hi> But we will ceaſe examples, and vrge the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> of the point, which are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> God is the <hi>beſt maſter</hi> we can ſerve, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have reaſon to goe about his ſervice the <hi>firſt</hi> thing we doe, when once we can doe any thing at all. That he is our <hi>beſt maſter,</hi> appeareth not only in his <hi>nature,</hi> he being every way infinitely good, but alſo in his infinite <hi>favour,</hi> which sheweth it ſelf, both in that he gives vs the <hi>beſt worke,</hi> and the <hi>beſt wages</hi> in the world. Our <hi>worke</hi> is to worship and obey him, and to doe <hi>only</hi> thoſe things which are <hi>beſt</hi> for our ſelves, whereby we may be moſt happy in our ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, both being at peace with him, and enjoying all things in a ſanctified and ſweete eſtate. Our <hi>wages</hi> (beſides his manifolde mercyes here) is all inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable bleſſednes, that heaven can afford vs, the glory of that kingdome, wherein we shalbe <hi>glorious kings</hi> with himſelf for ever and ever. Now what would any man doe <hi>firſt, that</hi> were guided but by naturall reaſon? even that which he might benefit moſt by, Beholde then here is.</p>
            <list>
               <item>the <hi>beſt maſter</hi> that can be <hi>deſired</hi>
               </item>
               <item>the <hi>beſt ſervice</hi> that can be <hi>performed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>the <hi>beſt wages</hi> that can be <hi>received.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Let any reaſonable man judge whether he have not <hi>reaſon</hi> to ſet himſelfe ſo ſoone as is poſſible to this truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> they are like to proue his <hi>beſt</hi> ſervants, that begin <hi>ſoonest</hi> to ſerve him, for why? our <hi>firſt</hi> abilityes are <hi>freest</hi> from ſin, and leaſt taynted with evill, and ſoe much more apt, and able to good, then when once
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20805:13"/>they have beene habituated, and ſoaked, and ſeaſoned nay poyſoned, with <hi>astuall impiety,</hi> aded to that <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall impurity,</hi> which is in vs, and by both theſe, made <hi>vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnmeete</hi> for the Lord, as they cannot but be, when once <hi>Satan</hi> hath got in, and had the <hi>firſt hanſell</hi> of our harts, and ſoe poſeſt vs of a childe, that we have beene his vaſſalls, in the baſe, and hellish bondage of ſin and rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt God: it is hard getting of him <hi>out,</hi> if he be once <hi>in</hi> poſſeſſion, more hard, if he have beene <hi>in, longe.</hi> But if the Lord enter vs at <hi>first,</hi> we are his for <hi>ever,</hi> he cannot be gotten <hi>out</hi> by all the devills in hell, if once he have the happy poſſeſſion of our harts, he will holde <hi>his owne.</hi> Seing therefore we are <hi>fittest</hi> for him in our <hi>first</hi> times, let vs know, it is goodreaſon we should <hi>then</hi> give our ſelves vnto him, eſpecially conſidering we can never (at the <hi>beſt</hi> we can be) come any thing neere that fitnes which once we had, when we were <hi>full</hi> of that created grace wherof we ſpake before.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> our firſt fruits muſt of neceſſity be beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, and employed one way or other, to <hi>good</hi> or to <hi>evill;</hi> to <hi>God</hi> or to the <hi>Devill,</hi> it cannot be avoyded but <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>two,</hi> muſt have the vſe of vs from the <hi>firſt</hi> time we are fit for any thing. We muſt needes belong either to the <hi>one,</hi> or to the <hi>other;</hi> religion tell's vs we cannot belong to <hi>both,</hi> and let <hi>reaſon</hi> ſpeake to which of the <hi>two,</hi> it is beſt belonging: I ſay let <hi>reaſon</hi> ſpeake, for no man can be ſoe vnreaſonable, as to make any doubt, or the leaſt demurre vpon it. If the Lord have vs, it is <hi>that</hi> he would have, if the devill get vs, woe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, we muſt account with God, for all the ſervice we have done him, even for every act, &amp; when this heavy account is made vp, we muſt vndergoe Gods eternall
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20805:13"/>curſe for our ſervice, and receive the hire of our worke with <hi>him</hi> (whome we have ſerved) in <hi>hell,</hi> where the worme never dyeth, and the <hi>fire</hi> never goeth out.</p>
            <p>Soe that, inaſmuch as our <hi>first</hi> fruits muſt goe to <hi>one</hi> of theſe, and that it will be ſoe miſerable with vs, if <hi>Satan</hi> ſeize vpon vs, let vs beleeve the truth of our doctrine and doe accordingly.</p>
            <p>I, (will ſome ſay) that is a good <hi>motion,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
               </label> and well it were with vs if we could doe as you ſay, but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, it is not in our power <hi>now,</hi> true it is, that <hi>once</hi> it was, but it is as true, that <hi>now</hi> it is not, and that is well knowne, yea <hi>too</hi> well, to our ſelves, and to God; how then would you have vs doe herein? doth God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what he knowe's we cannot doe? doe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts contayne <hi>jmpoſsibilityes?</hi> will he have vs vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take that which we are not able.</p>
            <p>I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> all that can be pleaded (though never ſoe <hi>truly</hi>) cannot on our part <hi>nullify</hi> any truth of God taught vnto vs, any precept of God impoſed on vs: ſoe long as all that we would <hi>excuſe</hi> our ſelves by, is long of our ſelves, and that whereby the Lord may <hi>accuſe</hi> vs moſt juſtly, becauſe (of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> without <hi>him</hi>) we fell from our <hi>perfection,</hi> and <hi>power</hi> we had, to give all duty to him at <hi>all times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, and too true, that we cannot give our ſelves <hi>now</hi> from our <hi>first,</hi> as we could have done in our created ſtate, but what of that? doth our <hi>jmbecility</hi> weaken the <hi>neceſsity</hi> of this duty? is Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ever the weaker becauſe we are worſe then we were, whan he gave his? can our corruption cancell or abate any jot or title of his truth? Noe, it doth, and will ſtand in full power, force, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20805:14"/>vertue againſt vs: we have <hi>enfeebled,</hi> and <hi>vnfitted</hi> our ſelves for God, but <hi>his</hi> law, <hi>his</hi> will is as abſolute and as ſtrong as ever, his counſell muſt <hi>ſtand</hi> though we <hi>fall,</hi> he is all <hi>one</hi> in commanding, though we be not <hi>ſoe</hi> in obeying; it is <hi>we</hi> with whome the <hi>caſe is altred,</hi> not <hi>he,</hi> for he is <hi>[Iehovah and changeth not.]</hi> He neede not, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he pleaſe (for he is noe way tyed by any neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) to take notice of our inabylity, if he doe, he may the more righteouſly reprove, and vpbrayd vs; if he doe not ſoe, it is his greater favour, not to caſt it in our teeth. He may to this day expect, (and therefore much more command) that every one of vs should be as <hi>Adam</hi> was at his <hi>beſt,</hi> &amp; condemne and plague vs for our vnfruitfullnes, if we be not: as Chriſt did curſe the fig tree for want of fruit,
<note place="margin">Mark. 11.13.</note> though it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſayd by one Evangeliſt that <hi>[the time of figs was not yet]</hi> that is, <hi>that time</hi> which ordinarily, <hi>now</hi> vnder nature <hi>corrupted,</hi> it did vſually beare fruit; it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth (nay it is more ceartaine) that before the earth was curſed, all fruits should have beene more <hi>frequent</hi> and <hi>abundant,</hi> yea, almoſt <hi>continuall</hi> (as ſome have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) like the trees in the paradice of God.
<note place="margin">Reu. 22.2</note> And ſoe our Saviour to shew, not only his <hi>power,</hi> but his <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes,</hi> curſed it, becauſe it was not ſoe fruitfull, as it was by creation, taking no notice of the vnfruitfullnes of it, or of the want of fruit which came to paſſe at this time of the yeare, by reaſon of the curſe through our corruption. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> And thus may he deale with vs, for that we are not at <hi>all</hi> times fruitfull in thoſe graces, of his good ſpirit, wherewith <hi>once</hi> he furnished vs, and made vs, meete and able <hi>(at any time)</hi> to honour him. What hath he to doe with our falling, and inſufficiency to doe his will? that lyeth betweene the <hi>devill,</hi> and <hi>vs,</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20805:14"/>anſwer, the Lord hath no hand in it, nor cannot be <hi>taxed</hi> with it in any reſpect, he commande's no more then he made vs <hi>fit</hi> for. So that there is no objecting this, to any <hi>good</hi> end, vnleſſe it be (as it ought to be) to humble vs, for that we are not, as we were <hi>once</hi> (and should have beene <hi>ever</hi>) and therevpon diſcerning our inability, to doe the Lord all the duty we owe him from our <hi>firſt</hi> breath; as alſo, ſeing by abſolute right, he may as well challenge it of vs, as of the <hi>first Adam;</hi> we herevpon beſtirre our ſelves the more, and the better, to haſten both our ſelves and others, vnto the practiſe of this inſtruction, and ſoe turne all this (by the power of <hi>grace</hi>) into a <hi>provocation,</hi> which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <hi>nature</hi> (perverſly) vrgeth as an <hi>objection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus the point is proved, and this ſcruple, (or cavill rather) removed, let vs now come to the <hi>vſes</hi> of of the point, which are <hi>three,</hi> and doe concerne all ſorts of men: to wit.</p>
            <list>
               <item>the <hi>children</hi> of God, for <hi>conſolation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>the <hi>vngodly,</hi> for <hi>reprehenſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>all <hi>men,</hi> for <hi>inſtruction.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> And firſt for the ſaints, the ſons and daughters of God, it cannot be but exceeding happy &amp; comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them, who have <hi>harts</hi> convinced of this truth, and <hi>lives,</hi> that have expreſſed it, ſince the firſt day it was revealed to them from the Lord, before whome, they have ſincerely endeavoured, to give him the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of their <hi>knowledge</hi> of this <hi>leſſon,</hi> though, either through their owne <hi>perſonall</hi> ignorance therof, or through the error of <hi>parents</hi> in their education, they have not given him the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of their practiſe while they were in their non-age.</p>
            <p>It is a moſt happy thing to be <hi>rightly</hi> convicted of a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20805:15"/>divine truth, becauſe many are <hi>ſuperficially</hi> perſwaded, an will give a <hi>ſlight</hi> conſent, (&amp; <hi>leſſe,</hi> the Divell, if he be put to it, wil not doe) to many holy truthes of God, but <hi>they</hi> whome the Lord convinceth <hi>a right,</hi> (as he doth all his <hi>owne</hi>) he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth, in giving them, a harts reſolution ſetled in their very ſoules, to ſay within themſelves; <hi>this is the vndoubted truth of the euerliving God,</hi> thus, <hi>we muſt doe, &amp; endeavour to ſtire vp others to doe the ſame; and if it be a truth which we should haue</hi> practiſed before, <hi>we muſt repent for neglect</hi> paſt, <hi>&amp; be vpright with God for the</hi> time remayning, <hi>and goe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster becauſe we began ſoe late,</hi> and doe <hi>our</hi> beſt <hi>to draw others after vs, to that way which both they, and we should have gone,</hi> long before. He that is <hi>thus</hi> convicted, shall not goe long vncomforted.</p>
            <p>It is a ſimple impoſſibility, that men called at their <hi>ripe yeares,</hi> or in their <hi>age,</hi> should give their <hi>first</hi> fruits to the Lord, thoſe dayes are gone, and <hi>past:</hi> but to gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the Lord (at what time it pleaſeth him to call vs) the glory of <hi>this truth,</hi> in our ſounde perſwaſion, that it is <hi>thus,</hi> and ſingleharted humiliation, becauſe it had not place in our practiſe before <hi>now,</hi> &amp; moſt carefull provocation to our vtmoſt poſſibility, that it may be <hi>thus</hi> in <hi>ours,</hi> and all <hi>others,</hi> with whome, by any good meanes, we can prevayle, this is to be truly happy, and in a moſt comfortable condition, &amp; we are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God <hi>(thus doing)</hi> as if we had done it our ſelves from the firſt day of our life.</p>
            <p>How famous is <hi>Abraham, few</hi> men ſoe <hi>much</hi> renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in religion as he, <hi>none</hi> more, yet from his childe hood, he had not done ſervice, but to <hi>Satan</hi> in jdola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſuch other jmpiety, as vſually accompanieth that jniquity. But at the <hi>first call,</hi> he came, and aſſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20805:15"/>as he heard he did obey, and perceiving that the Lord had <hi>lost</hi> ſuch duty by him, as in his <hi>former</hi> dayes he should have received from him, he is <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vinced</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and reſolved, that his <hi>children</hi> shall give it, though his owne <hi>childe-hood,</hi> was given to ſin. And the diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>this</hi> in him, was <hi>that,</hi> that gave the <hi>Lord</hi> content, and <hi>Abraham</hi> comfort.</p>
            <p>Is not <hi>Moſes</hi> a man abundantly magnified, and that of God himſelf, as if he had beene (as indeede he was) ſome <hi>extraordinary ſervant</hi> of his, yet, for <hi>forty yeares</hi> of his life, what was he, (ſo farre as we finde?) but ſuch as others were that lived in the <hi>court</hi> of that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> Prince, who was the oppreſſor, and adverſary of Gods people; it may be, he might be <hi>leſſe groſſe,</hi> then ſome of his <hi>fellow courtiers,</hi> who were inclined to egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious jmpiety, but that he was <hi>good,</hi> or ſavoured of any ſaving <hi>grace,</hi> is more then appeareth to me. Howbeit inaſmuch as he freely and reſolutely, caſt off all the <hi>creddit,</hi> and <hi>profſit</hi> of his high dignity, &amp; preheminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in court, when the Lord would <hi>ſummon</hi> him to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve him, it was well taken, that from <hi>that age,</hi> and time, he wayted on the worke of God, though neither his <hi>childe-hood,</hi> nor <hi>youth</hi> were the Lords, in time paſt.</p>
            <p>What should I multiply <hi>more</hi> (as I might) of many other moſt worthy <hi>ſaints,</hi> who in the ſame <hi>caſe,</hi> have had the ſame <hi>comfort,</hi> what is <hi>over-past,</hi> and cannot be <hi>actually</hi> recovered, and performed, if it be rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, in our <hi>ſelues,</hi> and reformed in <hi>others</hi> (to our beſt power, it is <hi>all one,</hi> as if we had done it in our owne perſon. Let vs bewayle our owne want of <hi>duty</hi> and Gods want of <hi>glory</hi> by vs, and doe as <hi>Hannah</hi> did, for <hi>ſuch</hi> as may come within our poſſibility to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> off, or <hi>perſwade,</hi> namely, give them to the Lord from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20805:16"/>the <hi>first</hi> inſtant, that we have any intereſt in them, and it shalbe well with vs.</p>
            <p>And <hi>this</hi> I doe (of purpoſe) inſert here, becauſe <hi>Satan</hi> is malicious, and hungry, to <hi>gnaw</hi> vpon the very harts of Gods ſaints, when once he gett's <hi>a truth</hi> by the end, wherin, their time (for performance) is <hi>paſt,</hi> then doth he come with his <hi>pearceing</hi> temptations to wounde, and rende, the ſoules of ſuch as are ſingle harted, and to lay it in their dish, that <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> they should have done long ſince, God should have had their <hi>whole lives</hi> for his ſervice, now <hi>many yeares</hi> be gone, and there can be noe recalling of them, and can they thinke which way to make all well, when it is an vtter jmpoſſibility to recover <hi>one moment,</hi> much leſſe, many yeares: with <hi>theſe,</hi> and the like <hi>ſpight full,</hi> and greivous ſuggeſtions, he doth <hi>teaze,</hi> and <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> their gracious mindes to breede deſpayre in them.</p>
            <p>But now we are armed (I hope) to anſwer him, and that we may doe, and pay him <hi>double,</hi> both for <hi>himſelf,</hi> to whome we may ſay with joy and ſcorne; <hi>better once</hi> then <hi>never, for</hi> thy <hi>part,</hi> thy <hi>first dayes were as due to God as</hi> mine, <hi>but he will never</hi> call, <hi>but ever</hi> accurſe <hi>thee;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> and for <hi>our ſelves; but for</hi> my <hi>part, though I have lost my firſt dayes, my God will not loſe me ever, ſeing he call's once and be that come's then, comes time enough for</hi> mercy, <hi>though he should have came ſooner in</hi> duty: <hi>and moreover, know the Lord hath made many a happy man for his best ſervice, among thoſe who in their firſt dayes have beene fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſled: I greive, that I gave him not my childe-hood, or</hi> youth, <hi>but if he pleaſe to accept of</hi> my age <hi>I joy, and will joy, and doe my</hi> beſt <hi>to offer</hi> all <hi>that I can prevaile withall,</hi> aſſoone, <hi>as I should haue offered my ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20805:16"/>
            <p>Theſe and the like <hi>anſwers,</hi> will confound his <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills,</hi> and make him weary of vs: and he being thus reſiſted, our God and <hi>we,</hi> may be the more intimate and familiar; in the ſweeteſt paſſages of his ſinguler favour.</p>
            <p>And ſee we ſee there is ſounde comfort for ſuch as <hi>are</hi> perſwaded herof, and <hi>would</hi> have done it, and are <hi>humbled</hi> becauſe God hath beene robbed of his right in their minority.</p>
            <p>Againe; for ſuch as have offered their firſt fruits to the Lord, there comfort cannot be <hi>behinde</hi> (if it excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not) theirs that went <hi>before.</hi> Our <hi>A bell</hi> here, who was ſoe carefull to give the Lord the <hi>first</hi> of his <hi>flocke,</hi> and, (I cannot eaſily doubt but, that he gave the <hi>first</hi> of <hi>himſelf</hi> alſo) how doth the Lord magnify him in this his ſervice and duty? <hi>Did</hi> he not moſt graciouſly regard him and his offering? <hi>hath</hi> he not put it here into his owne booke to his perpetuall prayſe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4. 1. Joh. 3.</note> and not only <hi>here,</hi> but elſe-where in the <hi>new</hi> teſtament once and againe, that from the <hi>beginning</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> of the world, he might be famous, whereſoever either <hi>this, text,</hi> or <hi>thoſe,</hi> should be preached, that which he hath done, should not be forgotten? <hi>Did</hi> he not moſt dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply avenge his innocent blood vpon his jmpious bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made him the <hi>first</hi> and moſt fearfull <hi>ſpectacle</hi> of his juſtice, and malediction, to the <hi>terror</hi> of all ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding generations? And (which is <hi>more</hi> then all this) hath not the Lord <hi>crowned</hi> him with glory and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality in the heavens with himſelf, as well as <hi>renouned</hi> him for holynes, and piety here on earth?</p>
            <p>He is the <hi>first,</hi> whoſe ſoule every ſaw the face of God, noe man ever went from earth to heaven <hi>before him,</hi> among the innumerable ſpirits of juſt and perfect
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20805:17"/>men who now, and for ever live there with the Lord in glory. He was the firſt <hi>martyr,</hi> &amp; had the firſt <hi>crowne</hi> none every <hi>dyed</hi> for the Lord before him, none could <hi>liue</hi> with the Lord before him: he was the Lords firſt <hi>witnes,</hi> &amp; among all the Lords <hi>worthyes</hi> this righteous <hi>Abel</hi> (as Chriſt call's him) ſtood in the <hi>fore-frunt</hi> of the battell, &amp; shed <hi>the first blood</hi> for the <hi>faith,</hi> &amp; teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> before there was any to <hi>back</hi> or <hi>abett</hi> him.</p>
            <p>And as the Lord tooke great notice of this <hi>first,</hi> ſoe alſo, hath he done in like manner of the <hi>rest,</hi> who have began betime to be acquainted with him, in his ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. How came <hi>Samuell</hi> to be ſoe rare a man, and to be numbred among the moſt ſpeciall <hi>favourites</hi> of God, <hi>Moſes, Iob, Daniell, Noah,</hi> &amp;c? Why; doe you not remember what we have ſayd of his <hi>mother,</hi> how she gave him to God (in reſolution) <hi>before</hi> she had him and was as good as her word, aſſoone as he was <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</hi> doe you not remember what is ſayd of himſelf [<hi>the childe Samuell miniſtred before the Lord</hi>] the childe <hi>Samuell;</hi> this was worthy to be acounted <hi>wonderfull,</hi> that <hi>a childe</hi> should miniſter before the Lord, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally being <hi>ſo yong,</hi> that; as yet) he knew not the <hi>voyce</hi> or <hi>call</hi> of God, from <hi>Elyes,</hi> but ranne to <hi>Ely,</hi> once and againe, when the Lord called vpon him, about the <hi>first</hi> buſines he had to doe for him.</p>
            <p>What may be the cauſe that <hi>Ioſiah</hi> is ſoe <hi>mightily</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, that, as if he were <hi>matchleſſe</hi> it is ſayd of him, <hi>[that there was none like before him]</hi> nor any to ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that should be ſuch a <hi>one,</hi> as this peereleſſe prince was; true it is, that never any king, either of <hi>Jſraell</hi> or <hi>Iudah</hi> (no not among the <hi>good</hi> kings) before or after him, went <hi>ſoe farre</hi> in the worke of Godfor the purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; purifying of his worship, as <hi>he</hi> did; this king did
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20805:17"/>ſurmount them all: but how is it that <hi>he</hi> came to <hi>doe,</hi> what none had <hi>done,</hi> more then they all? why; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to worke the worke of God betime, &amp; that may be a mayne reaſon why he did ſo much: at <hi>eight yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re olde</hi> (ſaith the ſcripture) <hi>[he ſought the Lorde,
<note place="margin">2. King. 23.1.</note>]</hi> and that is but in childe-hood, all men know.</p>
            <p>What should I tell you of <hi>Solomon,</hi> of <hi>Timothie,</hi> and ſuch others as I might mention to this purpoſe; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more <hi>ſure,</hi> then this, that they have beene the <hi>rarest,</hi> and moſt excellent men, in piety, and religion, and the <hi>moſt able</hi> inſtruments of Gods honour, who in the <hi>beginning</hi> of their dayes, have <hi>begun</hi> to doe good, they muſt needes be <hi>neerest</hi> heaven, who ſet out on their way, <hi>ſooneſt,</hi> &amp; continue going on thither-warde.</p>
            <p>Only, it is <hi>ſeldome,</hi> that we ſee any enter vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſoe <hi>early</hi> now a dayes, they are very <hi>few,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be ſoe ſoone <hi>faith full.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> The <hi>more</hi> are they to be <hi>admired</hi> of godly men, and the <hi>more</hi> to be <hi>comforted</hi> of God, who are founde <hi>ſucklings</hi> in grace, aſſoone as they are <hi>weanelings</hi> in nature, and hang vpon Gods <hi>breasts,</hi> when they have given over they <hi>mothers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that by all that hath beene ſayd, it appeareth to be a <hi>happy thing,</hi> and they to be moſt <hi>happy men,</hi> who have learned <hi>this leſſon</hi> of the Lord, and walked accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>light</hi> therof, which leade's on directly in the way of <hi>life,</hi> wherin howſoever a man may <hi>(poſsibly)</hi> meete with ſome moleſtation, and <hi>miſery,</hi> yet the <hi>end</hi> of it will (vndoubtedly) be <hi>endles,</hi> &amp; infinite <hi>glory,</hi> with <hi>him,</hi> who wil make thoſe moſt glorious beyond <hi>all time</hi> who betooke themſelves to glorify him <hi>betime.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much might be ſpoken to enlarge their conſolation who have <hi>harts,</hi> to doe according to <hi>this</hi> inſtruction. But of this more hereafter: we now paſſe to our 2. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20805:18"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> And that concerneth all vngodly perſons, who howſoever they <hi>will</hi> (becauſe they <hi>muſt,</hi> and cannot for <hi>starke shame,</hi> ſay otherwiſe) after a ſort acknowledg this our <hi>doctrine</hi> to be true; yet walke (moſt wickedly) in a courſe farre <hi>wyde</hi> of it, nay, cleane <hi>contrary</hi> to it: their mouthes cannot be ſoe <hi>monstruouſly</hi> finfull, but they muſt confeſſe it to be a truth, howbeit, their hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish <hi>harts,</hi> and <hi>lives,</hi> doe deny it in their moſt jmpious practiſe all the dayes of their life: yea they have taught their tongues to lye herin notoriouſly, and that not to <hi>men</hi> alone, but to the <hi>Lord,</hi> of whome and of whoſe ſervice they vſe to ſay, <hi>it is not yet time, it may be time enough heareafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O yee impious children of the father of <hi>lyes,</hi> can you ſay it is true, that every one shoulde begin <hi>betime,</hi> and it were not amiſſe if it were <hi>ſoe,</hi> and yet tell God and men to their faces, that <hi>any time</hi> is time enought hereby, you shew your ſelves to be the very <hi>jmps</hi> of the devill, who hath taught you ſuch a <hi>language,</hi> as <hi>one part</hi> of your ſpeech confutes, nay confound's <hi>another,</hi> and ſuch <hi>a practiſe,</hi> as overturnes Gods <hi>truth</hi> which you dare not deny, and confirmes that <hi>falſhood</hi> which none ought to affirme: Miſerable ſoules, how are yee given over of God into the <hi>hands,</hi> nay into the <hi>bands</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> who if you ſpeake or breath out but <hi>one true word,</hi> can make your life, both to <hi>bely,</hi> and <hi>abolish</hi> that, and to ratify every <hi>jot,</hi> and <hi>tittle</hi> of thoſe infernall falshoodes, that he ſuggeſts into your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Doe yee not ſin <hi>preſumptuouſly,</hi> and againſt the light of your owne knowledg, and conſcience, that <hi>can thus</hi> ſpeake, and <hi>dare thus</hi> doe? and is <hi>ſuch</hi> a ſin a light mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or eaſy to anſwer to the judge of the whole worlde? know; you will not finde it ſoe, in the day of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20805:18"/>the great and vniverſall <hi>aſsize,</hi> when all flesh shall <hi>at once,</hi> ſtand before him to <hi>give</hi> account, and receive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, according to what they have done.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the <hi>world</hi> hath beene ever <hi>full</hi> (&amp; <hi>hell</hi> wilbe one day <hi>full,</hi> of ſoe many of them as repent not) of ſuch, as either turne God out of <hi>all time,</hi> or bring him in the <hi>tayle</hi> of all the time they live, and that houre of our <hi>life</hi> which fall's out to be ſoe neere <hi>death,</hi> that a man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither ſerue <hi>himſelf</hi> nor the <hi>world</hi> nor <hi>Satan,</hi> becauſe of extreme imbecility of body, is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for God, to ſerue him in, though it be but in ſaying <hi>Lord have mercy vpon me:</hi> And this they dreame to be enough to bring them to heaven, <hi>that,</hi> or their <hi>Pater noster,</hi> (if they can but have time to ſay it) will make them <hi>happy enough,</hi> they care for <hi>no more,</hi> and ſoe (poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſooles) they goe like <hi>oxen</hi> to the ſlaughter, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> words ſpeaking, will purchaſe Gods glorious kingdome, and poſeſſe them of it, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout any <hi>more a doe.</hi> Which jmagination, is <hi>more</hi> blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous then ever came into a <hi>Papiſts</hi> apprehenſion, for as <hi>groſſe</hi> as they are, in the matter of <hi>merit,</hi> yet they are not ſoe <hi>foule,</hi> as to ſay that <hi>glory</hi> may be gotten with ſoe <hi>ſlight</hi> deſert, nay they exhort men to doe good works <hi>betime,</hi> and abundantly; I never read any of them that helde, heaven might be had for a few <hi>bare words,</hi> eſpecially, proceeding from a minde, and ſoule, <hi>more ſicke,</hi> then at the <hi>pangs</hi> of death the body can be.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>pestilent</hi> conceit of prorogeuing time with God, is a vniverſall diſeaſe, and hath <hi>ſlayne</hi> many that are <hi>gone,</hi> and <hi>infected</hi> deſperately millions of men that yet <hi>liue</hi> in the chriſtian worlde. Every one throwe's off the <hi>day</hi> of this duty, &amp; breake's that commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20805:19"/>in the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> which they were bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in the <hi>shaddow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 22.29.20.</note> where God ſaith <hi>[Thou shalt not delay to offer thy firſt fruits] whether of oxen, &amp; cattell, of liquor or any other thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delay,</hi> is a thing that the Lord ſtill deteſted in any thing that he had for vs to doe he would never endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re <hi>protraction</hi> of time; he hath ever pleaded with his people for <hi>haſte,</hi> and expedition, and for <hi>priority</hi> befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all things yea, to be put in the <hi>firſt place</hi> before all things, as well he doth deſerue to be, in the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the <hi>corrupteſt</hi> man among chriſtians. And albeit, that both theſe be ſoe, that the Lord hath ſoe <hi>loved</hi> to be <hi>firſt</hi> ſerved, and <hi>loathed</hi> in his ſoule to be ſet <hi>behin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> yet, as if prolonging, and poaſting off the piactiſe of piety, were a thing that would rather make vs <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> to the Lord, then <hi>deteſtable</hi> in his ſight: the divill (who is both Gods, and our <hi>avowed</hi> adverſary herin) doth not only perſwade jmpious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to ſtay, &amp; <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe</hi> whatſoever is required of them in true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but alſo, he puts into their mindes, and mouthes what to <hi>plead</hi> againſt God, &amp; their owne <hi>best good,</hi> (but they litle know it) in the truth of this point which we now vrge, &amp; arme's them to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mouth with ſtrange <hi>inſolency</hi> againſt heaven, to defend their <hi>double</hi> jmpie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in deviſing <hi>damnable</hi> shifts to ſupport them therin, that they may be ſtill, and (for ever,) holden faſt in the <hi>cordes</hi> of their jniquity, and <hi>linger</hi> ſoe long in their ſinfull courſes, and accurſed carriage, till <hi>time</hi> shalbe no more, and it be too <hi>late</hi> to wish for the day of <hi>grace</hi> the day of Gods <hi>patience,</hi> and our <hi>repentance,</hi> which being now paſt &amp; gone, we are to beare for ever, the righteous vengeance of the wretched neglect of that happy <hi>opportunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20805:19"/>
            <p>It is a ſure thing that <hi>Satan</hi> never helpe's man to a <hi>jmpious hart</hi> to doe an evill, but he alſo help's him to an <hi>jmpudent mouth</hi> to defend the ſin he doth:
<note place="margin">Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for putting of Gods ſervice.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his pretences are <hi>ſuch,</hi> and doe ſeeme ſoe <hi>plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> as that they doe miſleade the moſt part of men in the worlde, let vs looke into them a litle, and <hi>try</hi> whether they be <hi>currant,</hi> or <hi>counterfeit, pure</hi> or <hi>haſe,</hi> by the trueſt <hi>touch-stone,</hi> even the word of God, which is truth it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But before we come to any particulers, let vs <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> a few words in generall to all ſuch as doe plead any thing in this particuler, to the end and purpoſe afore ſayd; let them therefore know, and receive for a <hi>memorandum</hi> thus much.</p>
            <p>That all that they ſpeake is <hi>againſt</hi> God, and their owne eternall <hi>good:</hi> and that it is <hi>for</hi> the, Devill and his advantage to their owne everlaſting <hi>evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all this <hi>plea,</hi> what are they? <hi>Adverſaryes</hi> to God, and themſelves; and <hi>Advocates</hi> for the <hi>Divell</hi> againſt themſelves. But let vs heare them ſpeake, although, <hi>all</hi> they ſpeake, be not worth the <hi>hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ſay (though God ſay the contrary, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves confeſſe it too) that though men should begin <hi>betime,</hi> and it were well if they would, yet there is no ſuch <hi>neceſsity</hi> lying vpon it, that we should be ſoe <hi>nice</hi> vpon it: And why?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea. </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe (<hi>as they curſedly conceit</hi>) a man may make <hi>too much haste,</hi> too much a doe, and what neede one be ſoe curious, &amp; <hi>preciſe,</hi> at preſent, there is <hi>time enough</hi> (for theſe matters) heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>This is their firſt <hi>Plea.</hi> Wherin, I muſt be bolde to aske theſe men <hi>first,</hi> whether they ſpeake (when they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20805:20"/>thus ſpeake) as they thinke, or not. If not, what hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish <hi>hypocriſy</hi> is it in any man to <hi>belye</hi> his owne <hi>minde,</hi> with his owne <hi>mouth?</hi> what wofull impiety is it, to vtter that (in <hi>others</hi> hearing) which a mans <hi>owne</hi> hart doth contradict within himſelf? If they doe thinke as they ſay (which I thinke every man would be well adviſed before he would doe, if he knew <hi>all</hi>) then let vs ſee if we can shew them, what <hi>blaſphemy</hi> is wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vp in this ſpeach, inaſmuch as the ſcope therof is guilty of the fearfulleſt <hi>fellony</hi> that (almoſt) may be committed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>God is robbed</hi> by them of his right, in the duty of their owne, and the <hi>firſt dayes</hi> of ſuch other, as they doe <hi>thus</hi> delude. <hi>They</hi> are <hi>robbed</hi> by <hi>Satan</hi> (but with their owne conſent, for they plead for the <hi>theife</hi>) of that right which Chriſt Ieſus hath purchaſed for ſuch as are obedient to his truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Others</hi> alſo are <hi>robbed</hi> of the ſame good, by vttering theſe vngodly ſayings, to ſeduce them, ſinfully to <hi>ſett off</hi> the time of their turning to the Lord. And I thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the man that knew this, would not be ſo <hi>free</hi> of theſe words, which are ſoe <hi>wofull</hi> as we ſee, were there noe more to be ſayd againſt them.</p>
            <p>But let vs come neerer,
<note place="margin">The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of it</note> and <hi>pry</hi> more narrowly into this plea, and the further we goe, the more foule <hi>abhomination</hi> shall we finde, and detect therin, and that in <hi>divers</hi> reſpects, a <hi>few</hi> wherof, we will notify be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>1</label> 1. This plea, ſuppoſeth an abſolute <hi>cearteinety</hi> of more time yet to come, and to be <hi>remayning,</hi> vnto our lives: why should any man (in common ſence) ſay it is <hi>time enough heareafter,</hi> if he were not (as he thinks) aſſured of more time to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20805:20"/>come after-warde.</p>
            <p>Now thus to ſurmize is groſſe ſin, inaſmuch as the Lord hath taught vs to know, that we cannot <hi>expect</hi> much leſſe <hi>warrant,</hi> one inſtant of time, or a moment more to breath in, then we doe already enjoy.
<note place="margin">Tro. 27.1. Iam. 4.14</note> Doth not the wiſe man tell vs, <hi>[we know not what a day shall bring forth?]</hi> Doth not the Apoſtle ſay as much for to morrow? <hi>[you know not what shalbe to morrow?]</hi> Was it not the <hi>fooles</hi> ſaying in the Goſpell <hi>[ſoule take thy eaſe, eate, drinke, and be merry, then hast enough in store for many yeares]</hi> loe, he dreamed of many <hi>dayes,</hi> nay <hi>yeares,</hi> yea he preſumed vpon <hi>both,</hi> when he had not <hi>one day</hi> more to live out of <hi>hell,</hi> fulfilling that of the Prophet. <hi>[Deſtruction shall come vpon the wicked, and he shall not know the morning therof]</hi> yet will theſe vngodly perſons be preſumeing of <hi>more</hi> time, and of time <hi>enough,</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reafter. Noe, noe, we have not ſpent our time <hi>past,</hi> ſoe well, as that we may vndertake for <hi>more</hi> to come; had any man dealt with vs as we have dealt with God, I aſſure my ſelf he should not live <hi>a day</hi> to an <hi>end,</hi> if we had power to <hi>hang</hi> him vp: the more wickedly doe they carry themſelves againſt the Lord, who having <hi>long ſince,</hi> deſerved to <hi>hang</hi> in hell fire, for not hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him <hi>heretofore,</hi> dare yet ſay, there is time for that <hi>hearcafter:</hi> as if we were <hi>Gods,</hi> to fore-ſee, &amp; had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg of future things; the which to arrogate, is extreame jmpiety. This is the <hi>first,</hi> but not the <hi>worst,</hi> of this plea, Let vs ſurvey a ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>2</label> 2. This plea ſuppoſeth, nay preſumeth, not only that there wilbe more time ſimply, but (which is more) more time of <hi>grace,</hi> more and better opportunity of repentance, &amp; turning to God, then the <hi>preſent</hi> is.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20805:21"/>
            <p>And this is worſe then the former, and much more egregious in the ſight of God: for howſoever every dayes experience doth witneſſe in the courſe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and all things naturall, that have life doe teſtify, that the Lord is pleaſed to beſtow life &amp; being vpon creatures, and that (amonge <hi>men</hi>) as well vpon the <hi>vnjuſt</hi> as the <hi>just,</hi> the <hi>infidell,</hi> as the <hi>faithfull:</hi> Yet that together with this, time of <hi>grace</hi> should be preſumed vpon, and taken for granted by any mortall man (that is willingly <hi>graceleſſe),</hi> and thruſts off, the call of God, and his heavenly <hi>proffer</hi> of the ſame; is a thing ſoe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and ſenceleſſe, ſoe ſinfull and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and an act of ſuch <hi>arrogancy</hi> againſt the Lord, as he will ſeverely <hi>punish,</hi> and noe way <hi>cherish,</hi> in the hart of man.</p>
            <p>What? doth the naturall <hi>ſunne</hi> in the firmament, &amp; the <hi>ſunne</hi> of <hi>righteouſnes,</hi> keepe both one courſe every day and houre? are the <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>precious</hi> things of God that pertaine to our beſt being, &amp; the <hi>common</hi> benefits of the earth, both at one <hi>rate?</hi> and to be had <hi>alike</hi> at all times? The ſunne in the firmament hath beene <hi>rarely</hi> interrupted in her courſe; but the <hi>ſunne</hi> of righteouſnes hath <hi>many a time</hi> beene <hi>darkened</hi> in divers places, nay quite <hi>remooved</hi> from ſome places: The former is for all <hi>times</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons,</hi> the latter is for <hi>ſeaſons</hi> only, not tyed to all <hi>times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore is the Lord ſtill lying at vs and calling eagerly vpon vs, touching our <hi>awaking</hi> out of ſin, and <hi>betaking</hi> ourſelves to holynes, vpon this ground [<hi>And that conſidering the</hi> ſeaſon] <hi>For now the</hi> ſeaſon <hi>is come. [This is the</hi> day <hi>of ſalvation, this is the acceptable</hi> ſeaſon <hi>To</hi> day: <hi>if yee will heare] while it is called</hi> to <hi>day</hi> with many more of the like every day in the <hi>yeare,</hi> is not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20805:21"/>the day of <hi>grace,</hi> every <hi>time,</hi> not the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> fit for this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Lord is not tyed or bound in <hi>duty,</hi> to give vs <hi>one</hi> day or ſeaſon, but if in <hi>mercy</hi> he pleaſe to offer ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me <hi>few,</hi> no men may looke for <hi>many;</hi> this gate is not <hi>ever open</hi> to every one, it is <hi>often shutt,</hi> nay,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.10.</note> it is <hi>ever shut</hi> to all ſuch as were not ready to goe in, when it was <hi>open.</hi> Gods <hi>calender</hi> and <hi>ours</hi> differ much, our dayes are <hi>constant,</hi> we can ceartainely foreſee a yeare (or more) before vs, when ſuch a time will come; it is <hi>not ſoe</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, the Lords <hi>almanacke</hi> gives noe ſuch light or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, his <hi>happy times,</hi> are hid from their eyes who were shewed them long <hi>ſince,</hi> but would not <hi>then,</hi> and shall not <hi>now,</hi> ſee them. Well may a ſinfull wretch fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſome <hi>ſaints dayes</hi> there; that is, to his confuſion, he may looke vpon the bleſſed ſeaſons, they have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vſe of, to give themſelves to the Lord, but his <hi>owne dayes</hi> he can finde none, but ſuch as be <hi>past,</hi> and all written in <hi>red</hi> letters, in letters of <hi>blood,</hi> for his blood is vpon <hi>himſelf,</hi> who hath neglected ſoe great ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> therof, and let the worke of God alone, till it be too late to goe about it. But let vs yet ſee ſomething further, what more will follow hence.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>3</label> 3. This plea is yet more foule in this <hi>third,</hi> then in <hi>both</hi> the former: for why? it doth not only preſume vpon <hi>time,</hi> and vpon time of <hi>grace,</hi> (and <hi>both</hi> without God); but more, it preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>to diſpoſe</hi> this time, and to order it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance at <hi>our pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein, what doe we? (ſurely we are not well adviſed, in it) is not this to vſurpe Gods place and prerogative?</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:20805:22"/>
            <p>We make our ſelves <hi>masters</hi> of the time, and of that which is to be done therin, as if we might not only take the time <hi>when we will,</hi> but alſo doe therin <hi>what we will,</hi> and as if it were now in our <hi>power,</hi> and at our <hi>pleaſure,</hi> to give our ſelves to God when we thinke good. Which apprehenſions are moſt <hi>proud</hi> in vs, and moſt <hi>vnpleaſing</hi> to him, being apparantly <hi>prejudiciall,</hi> to his wiſdome and providence wherby all our <hi>dayes,</hi> and all our <hi>wayes</hi> are ordered.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>goodnes</hi> we live and move <hi>naturally:</hi> in his <hi>mercy</hi> we live and move <hi>ſpiritually:</hi> in his <hi>power</hi> &amp; aſſiſtance, we doe any thing we ought that is <hi>heavenly:</hi> and shall we arrogate <hi>all three</hi> to our ſelves, without any colour of ground or reaſon, and take theſe things ſoe <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> (or rather ſoe <hi>hellishly</hi>) vpon vs, as if we were <hi>equall</hi> with God, yea, <hi>aboue</hi> him, rather, to diſpoſe <hi>that time</hi> to our ſelves, and in <hi>that time,</hi> to diſpoſe our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to <hi>that</hi> ſervice, which (for our owne former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt) the Lord doth, and wil, deny vs in <hi>both?</hi> that neither we shall have time to <hi>breath,</hi> or if we have, that yet no <hi>breath</hi> of ſpirituall life shalbe in vs, to move towards any thing that is acceptable in his ſight.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>betters</hi> have had better mindes, who have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that without him, we could <hi>be nothing;</hi> without him, we could <hi>have nothing;</hi> without him, we could <hi>doe nothing:</hi> and vpon theſe thoughts, have caſt all good things vpon his <hi>wiſdome</hi> to diſpoſe, his <hi>power</hi> to bring to paſſe, his loving <hi>kindnes</hi> and favour to encreaſe, and encourage in vs: acknowledging both <hi>themſelves,</hi> and their <hi>times</hi> to be in his hands. It would well become <hi>theſe</hi> that thus plead, to practiſe the ſame, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they doe not, we ſee what jmpiety they incurre herin; yet is not this <hi>all,</hi> more remayneth.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:20805:22"/>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>4</label> 4. This plea <hi>of time enough heareafter,</hi> &amp; <hi>of making too much hast yet,</hi> argueth that theſe perſons doe thinke theſe <hi>two things</hi> to be true.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. that <hi>God</hi> may be ſerved <hi>too long.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. that the <hi>Divell</hi> may be ſerved <hi>too litle.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Both which doe as naturally flow from their <hi>foule,</hi> and <hi>jmpure</hi> mouthes, as water from a fountayne; for wherto <hi>els</hi> can their ſayings tende, ſeing (as we ſayd before) either <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Divell,</hi> muſt be ſerved of vs at all times, and <hi>vntill</hi> we have ſacrificed our ſelves to the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>Divell</hi> hath <hi>all</hi> our dayes.</p>
            <p>And may we thinke that heaven <hi>can,</hi> or <hi>will,</hi> heare, and beare, the hydeous <hi>blaſphemy</hi> of both theſe, or either of them? what? may we ſerve the Lord <hi>too ſoone?</hi> and, <hi>too ſoone</hi> give over the ſervice of <hi>Satan?</hi> is the divell become the better <hi>maſter,</hi> and God the <hi>worſe,</hi> that our <hi>laſt time,</hi> may ſerve his turne, and all the <hi>reſt,</hi> litle enough for the other? who hath heard ſuch things among the <hi>heathens,</hi> or ſuch ſpeeches as doe, as directly, and plainely inferre and conclude them, as if they did ſpeake them? <hi>How</hi> vnreaſonable, <hi>how</hi> irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, are both? nay, how excecrable is either of the <hi>two</hi> by it ſelf? the one <hi>applaude's</hi> the Divell <hi>aboue God,</hi> the other <hi>abaſes</hi> the Lord <hi>below</hi> the divell, <hi>will</hi> either; <hi>can</hi> both be ſufered? were not the <hi>patience</hi> of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty <hi>infinite,</hi> theſe ſinners would ſink into <hi>hell,</hi> yea, into the <hi>nethermost hell,</hi> but let them know; <hi>forbearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> is no <hi>acquittance;</hi> he that <hi>doth endure this</hi> ſoe long, will in the end avenge it, with the heavieſt juſtice and wrath, that is
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>revealed</hi> from heaven, or</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>reſerved</hi> in hell</item>
               </list> 
               <hi>as</hi> againſt all other, <hi>ſoe</hi> eſpecially, againſt this <hi>mighty</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20805:23"/>vngodlines of men, then which what can be more <hi>monstrous</hi> or provoking, to draw ſwift damnation vpon their ſoules that <hi>thus</hi> ſpeake: for what can be ſpoken to the <hi>greatest diſgrace</hi> of him that is <hi>most</hi> glorious, if this be not? and can we once <hi>ſurmize,</hi> that the Lord will ſuffer ſuch indignity and diſparagemet at our hands &amp; not power out his indignation vpon vs? Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, if withall, we well conſider, our <hi>owne</hi> jujury we doe our <hi>ſelves,</hi> beſides this jmpiety againſt the Lord: becauſe the <hi>leſſe</hi> ſervice we doe the Lord, and the <hi>more</hi> we doe the divell, the more wofull is it for vs, in both <hi>reſpects:</hi> for that <hi>litle</hi> we would give God is <hi>rejec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> that we doe for <hi>Satan</hi> is <hi>plagued,</hi> and ſo by <hi>both,</hi> we are wrapt vnder the eternall wrath of his dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adfull majeſty.</p>
            <p>Thus and no <hi>better,</hi> then we have ſayd, but much <hi>worſe,</hi> then we <hi>can</hi> ſay, is the ſequell of this firſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>apologie,</hi> which men make againſt God, and their owne ſoules, in the <hi>procrastination</hi> of the power, and practiſe of this truth. Now if a man should ſumme vp all theſe together, would not the <hi>totall,</hi> be <hi>terrible</hi> (thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke you) to the ſoule that is guilty in the <hi>Items?</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>to aſſure our ſelves of more <hi>time of life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>to preſume that ſome of <hi>that,</hi> shalbe <hi>time of grace.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>to take vpon vs to diſpoſe of that time, what <hi>we will doe</hi> therin.</item>
               <item>to jmagine God may have too <hi>much,</hi> and the divell too <hi>litle,</hi> of our ſervice.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Is any <hi>one</hi> of theſe anſwerable before God? much leſſe are they <hi>all</hi> excuſable: noe noe, every of them is <hi>high treaſon</hi> againſt
<list>
                  <item>his <hi>honour</hi> who order's <hi>all time.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:20805:23"/>
                  <item>his <hi>favour</hi> who gives all time of <hi>grace.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>his excellency and <hi>worthines,</hi> who deſerues the duty of all our dayes.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words muſt be <hi>eaten,</hi> and <hi>recalled,</hi> and that with more then ordinary humiliation, greife, and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation; or nothing can remayne but his juſt vengean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce vpon the tranſgreſſors; it is moſt true of <hi>this plea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 1.23.</note> which <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſpake of <hi>Adoniahs</hi> deſire, that <hi>[he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this word against his owne life],</hi> and was thervpon inſtantly ſlayne: and ſoe might <hi>they</hi> be, who have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken theſe words againſt their owne <hi>eternall life:</hi> and if the Lord should now ſeize vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them to everlaſting <hi>death,</hi> how righteous were it vpon theſe vngodly wretches? againſt whome the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith, the Lord will come in great glory, and dreadfull power, even (<hi>among</hi> other things) [<hi>for their hard</hi> and curſed <hi>ſpeakings</hi>] of which number, who can jmagine that <hi>theſe</hi> are not? <hi>what neede ſuch hast? there is time enough hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reafter for theſe matters:</hi> wofull man, that vttereſt <hi>theſe</hi> words; is there ſoe litle neede that <hi>God</hi> should have his <hi>glory,</hi> that <hi>thou</hi> shouldſt (by giving it) be truly <hi>happy?</hi> if thy <hi>whole</hi> time were given to God, were it <hi>enough?</hi> nay can <hi>any time</hi> be enough for his duty? ſuppoſe <hi>one man</hi> might live from one <hi>end</hi> of the world to the <hi>other,</hi> from the <hi>first</hi> day to the <hi>laſt</hi> of all time, to ſee both the <hi>creation</hi> and <hi>conſummation</hi> of all things, yea, and admit that man could live without <hi>ſin</hi> too, and not miſcarry one <hi>moment,</hi> but be evermore doing that which might honour God? could <hi>this man</hi> ſay he had given God <hi>enough?</hi> I trow not: for <hi>what</hi> time can be (in equity) enough for him, whoſe <hi>least glory</hi> to his ſaints shalbe infinite, and eternall <hi>beyond all time?</hi> and yet theſe accurſed mouthes, dare ſtint the Lord to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20805:24"/>
               <hi>laſt,</hi> and <hi>least,</hi> and <hi>worst,</hi> time of their life, and thinke it <hi>enough</hi> to. The Lord deliver vs (ſaith the apoſtle) from <hi>[vnreaſonable and wicked men,]</hi> which if <hi>theſe</hi> be not, <hi>who</hi> are, or can be?</p>
            <p>Oh then, let vs <hi>revoke, recant,</hi> and <hi>cancell</hi> preſently, what we have ſpoken <hi>wickedly; byte</hi> that tongue that vttered them, <hi>ſmite</hi> that hart that thought them; <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe</hi> and excecrate that divell that ſuggeſted them; leaſt our not revoking of them, <hi>rende</hi> vs from God, <hi>ſend</hi> vs to <hi>Satan,</hi> the author of them. Let vs lay our hands vpou our mouthes and reſolve never to open them againe to ſuch jmpious purpoſe, wherin.</p>
            <list>
               <item>the Lord of heaven is <hi>damnifyed:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>the ſoules of men are <hi>damned:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>the divell only is <hi>advantaged.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> is dishonoured, <hi>we</hi> are vndone, the <hi>divell</hi> goe's away with <hi>all</hi> the <hi>gaynes</hi> from <hi>both;</hi> which he could never doe, if he could not thus <hi>line</hi> the <hi>lips,</hi> and <hi>tip</hi> the <hi>tongues</hi> of ſome prophane perſons, to become his <hi>trumpets,</hi> to gather men to <hi>damnation,</hi> by ſuch <hi>deluſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>firſt</hi> infernal plea, that is deviſed, and vrged to deceive the Lord of his <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of our time, but have they done? when they have ſayd thus? noe they have, yet, a <hi>ſecond</hi> pretence, and a <hi>third</hi> too, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Let vs exanime the former.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Preten∣ce. </seg>2</label> 2. They plead, that in <hi>age,</hi> this worke may be done <hi>well</hi> enough, and <hi>time</hi> enough; then men are ſtayed and know what they doe, is it not fit for young <hi>giddy</hi> heads to meddle with ſuch matters.</p>
            <p>Then there wilbe more leaſure, when thoſe dayes come, wherin men have given over the proffits, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20805:24"/>and vanityes, of the world, and have nothing to doe, but to goe to church, and ſerve God. This they pretend.
<note place="margin">The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills of it.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but though in the <hi>former</hi> there was <hi>much,</hi> in this <hi>latter</hi> there is much <hi>more</hi> preſumption: we will try it, &amp; then we shall ſee it, in the particulers; which are the apparant conſequents of this pretence, which (vpon due ſearch) we shall finde, not to be ſoe <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly plauſible,</hi> as they are <hi>really pernicious,</hi> &amp; damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>1</label> 1. It doth directly <hi>contradict</hi> the Lord in that which he ſaith, for he will have the <hi>first</hi> of our dayes (as we have heard,) theſe ſay, <hi>noe,</hi> it is not fit for young heads to intermeddle,</p>
            <p>Is not this to give God the <hi>lye,</hi> yea to make him <hi>a lyar,</hi> who will (therefore) have the <hi>first</hi> becauſe they are <hi>fittest</hi> for him? is not this to charge <hi>folly</hi> vpon him that is only <hi>wiſe?</hi> as if he had not wiſdome enough to chuſe <hi>that part</hi> of our dayes for his duty, wherin we are moſt meete to doe it; but we will take it vpon vs, to be <hi>wiſer</hi> then <hi>he,</hi> and aſſigne him a <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> better ſuiting this buſines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He</hi> ſaith he will have our <hi>firſt, we</hi> will give the <hi>last</hi> time to him: doth not this inferre, that he is farre <hi>wyde</hi> of the marke, and wonderfully <hi>over-ſeene,</hi> and that we only are in the <hi>right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then theſe <hi>two,</hi> to make the moſt true and wiſe God (I <hi>tremble to vtter</hi> it) a <hi>foole,</hi> and a <hi>lyar,</hi> theſe <hi>two</hi> I ſay, doe make vp the <hi>firſt</hi> jmpiety, of this <hi>ſecond plea:</hi> the vengeance &amp; juſtice due to <hi>either</hi> of which, (much more to <hi>both</hi>) is beyond myne, (or any creatures) ability, to expreſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>2</label> 2. This preſumeth vpon <hi>olde age,</hi> and make's no
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20805:25"/>queſtion to live to ſee thoſe dayes and yeares wherin men are <hi>ſoe</hi> accounted.</p>
            <p>And this thwarteth all Gods truth touching the <hi>vnceartaniety,</hi> and <hi>shortnes</hi> of mans life, ſoe often taught vs every where; noe, the lives of <hi>theſe</hi> men muſt be <hi>no</hi> vanityes, <hi>dreames,</hi> or <hi>vapours;</hi> nor compared <hi>to</hi> win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, <hi>to</hi> ſmoake, <hi>to</hi> nothings; they are during and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent for 60.70. or more yeares. Howbeit, how many have not lived ſo many <hi>houres,</hi> as they dreamed <hi>yeares,</hi> nor ſoe many <hi>dayes,</hi> as they accounted <hi>ſcores?</hi> the ſun hath shyned clearely vpon ſome in the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> who were become <hi>carcaſes,</hi> er'e the <hi>evening:</hi> and others have ſeene it ſet in the <hi>evening,</hi> whoſe eyes were ſunke er'e <hi>morning,</hi> and yet they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as <hi>likely to live,</hi> as long lyved, as any that thus ſpeake. Even <hi>moments</hi> have ſwept away <hi>millions</hi> of <hi>other</hi> men, yet <hi>theſe,</hi> muſt live many yeares, at leaſt, to be olde, (how, or when, should God have them, <hi>els</hi>) and as if God himſelfe were <hi>bounde,</hi> and had <hi>bounde</hi> all his creatures to their <hi>good behaviour,</hi> that they muſt be ſaved harmeleſſe from any meanes of <hi>short</hi> life, or <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine</hi> death, either they muſt be <hi>aged,</hi> or God muſt not have <hi>them:</hi> and ſure, I am perſwaded he is moſt willing to <hi>loſe</hi> them. But of this preſumption we ſayd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>before,</hi> therefore the leſſe shall ſerve <hi>here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>3</label> 3. Admit you might live to age, and were ſure, not to dye till you were very olde, are you ſure either to <hi>have a hart</hi> to <hi>giue</hi> your ſelf to God <hi>then,</hi> or that, God hath <hi>a hart</hi> to <hi>take</hi> you <hi>then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſuredly (if it be well look't into) there is <hi>no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> for either, but very <hi>much</hi> againſt both: for why? con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>first,</hi> for our owne harts: what <hi>aptnes,</hi> what <hi>ability,</hi> nay what <hi>poſſibility</hi> will, or can, there be in vs, vnto good, who have beene ſoak't, and ſteep't many yeares
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20805:25"/>In all ſin and jmpiety; what holynes? what purity? in thoſe <hi>parts</hi> of our <hi>bodyes,</hi> and <hi>powers</hi> of our <hi>ſoules,</hi> which hell hath poyſoned and envenomed all our dayes, &amp; are now full of deadly poyſon, the hart <hi>hardened,</hi> the conſcience <hi>vnconvinced,</hi> the judgment <hi>blinded,</hi> the affections <hi>earthly,</hi> the will <hi>rebellious,</hi> all, <hi>benummed,</hi> and vtterly voyd of any <hi>ſparke</hi> of that <hi>quickening ſpirit,</hi> which muſt turne a man to God: wherwith will ye come to the Lord? if you pray, it muſt be with a mouth <hi>furr'd</hi> with blaſphemy, with a minde <hi>fraught</hi> with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther jmpiety, whereto you have beene affected? what will yee <hi>giue him,</hi> but a ſoule, and a body that have both combyned to be <hi>rebells</hi> your whole life, againſt him, and is there any <hi>power</hi> in <hi>theſe</hi> to be given to the Lord, who have <hi>ſolde themſelves</hi> like <hi>Ahab, to ſin,</hi> and whome the Divell <hi>(the true owner now)</hi> will come, &amp; <hi>clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi> as his <hi>owne,</hi> long ſince due <hi>vnto him,</hi> &amp; therefore will not e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dure they should be give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to any other <hi>from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is againſt all humane reaſon, and common ſence, that a man ſoe <hi>jnvred</hi> to ſin, ſoe accuſtomed and <hi>habit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated</hi> to corruption, who hath conſumed his dayes in nothing but in dishonouring &amp; diſobeying the Lord, and <hi>never knew</hi> what belonged to the <hi>ſavour</hi> of ſaving <hi>grace,</hi> or to the <hi>beginning</hi> of any god worke, should now be able to <hi>begin</hi> and finish, that <hi>great</hi> worke of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelf vp to God, and that <hi>at</hi> and <hi>in,</hi> his owne <hi>ſet time.</hi> Noe, there goe's more to it then <hi>ſoe:</hi> it is no ſuch <hi>short</hi> worke, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>can</hi> be <hi>ſoe quick</hi> at it, eſpecially, <hi>thoſe</hi> that have beene ſo <hi>ſlow</hi> all their dayes before: it will aske <hi>longer</hi> time, and <hi>more</hi> a doe, before it be wel <hi>begun,</hi> then theſe <hi>ſotts</hi> doe conceit, doth belong to the <hi>middle,</hi> and <hi>both ends</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>God ſayth that no man can come to him <hi>except he he be drawne;</hi> theſe men (it ſeemes) will come to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20805:26"/>God, <hi>whether he will or noe,</hi> as if it were in their power <hi>to draw God to themſelves;</hi> but as he will not have his goodnes, and power ſoe much <hi>abuſed,</hi> as to be <hi>drawne to them;</hi> ſoe neither, wil he endure, to have their rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious and debauched life ſo much <hi>honoured,</hi> as now at laſt caſt, to <hi>draw them to him:</hi> but even let <hi>him</hi> alone with them, who hath had their <hi>childehood,</hi> and <hi>youth,</hi> to take their <hi>age</hi> too, and ſoe to have <hi>all</hi> to himſelf. <hi>Cuſtomary ſin</hi> is not ſoe lightly caſt off, it is bred in the <hi>bone,</hi> it will not be eaſy to get it out of the <hi>flesh,</hi> and that <hi>ſoe,</hi> as Gods <hi>ſpirit</hi> may inſtantly enter, as theſe doe moſt idlely apprehend.</p>
            <p>Againe conſider the <hi>ſecond,</hi> what <hi>hart can God have</hi> to accept of the divells <hi>reverſion,</hi> or the <hi>leavings</hi> of our lives? the <hi>doteage,</hi> the <hi>dog-dayes</hi> (as it were) of all the time we live. Let <hi>olde age</hi> be well conſidered, and the ſtate therof pondered, in our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and all other <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> that ſerve vs: is it not the <hi>only time,</hi> wherin we caſt off, our <hi>ſervants,</hi> or <hi>cattell,</hi> to <hi>baſer</hi> vſes, as being vnfit for <hi>ours?</hi> An olde <hi>ſervingman,</hi> now overworne and decrepite, and not fitt to attend his <hi>Lord</hi> any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ha's a licenſe to keepe <hi>an ale-houſe,</hi> or become's ſome <hi>tapster,</hi> and ſoe is made ſervile to every baſe <hi>pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companion:</hi> An olde <hi>horſe,</hi> of good <hi>pace,</hi> of great <hi>price,</hi> before, for the <hi>ſaddle,</hi> the <hi>coach,</hi> now to the <hi>myll,</hi> to the <hi>harrow,</hi> to any meane <hi>drudgery,</hi> and at laſt, to the <hi>dogs.</hi> And can <hi>this age,</hi> wherin <hi>one man</hi> is not fit for <hi>anothers</hi> ſervice, nor any <hi>beaſt</hi> for <hi>mans</hi> vſe, be the <hi>meeteſt time</hi> for the moſt high, to be ſerved in of vs? what shall we then thinke to become <hi>his,</hi> when we are a burden to the <hi>world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 19 35.</note> and to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and both <hi>weary</hi> of one another as <hi>Barzillai</hi> ſpake to <hi>David,</hi> of himſelf?</p>
            <p>What man would be ſoe vſed by his <hi>beast,</hi> as theſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20805:26"/>men (more vnreaſonable then <hi>beaſts,</hi> herin) would vſe God: Admitt a manns beaſt (like <hi>Balams aſſe</hi>) could ſpeake, if he should ſay to his <hi>master</hi> (as theſe doe to the <hi>almighty.</hi>) While I am <hi>yonge</hi> and <hi>ſtrong,</hi> I muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my pleaſure, you muſt give me leave till my <hi>olde dayes,</hi> and then I wilbe <hi>yours</hi> to command, and give my ſelf wholy to <hi>your ſervice.</hi> What would the owner anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, thinke you? would he yeeld to his <hi>beaſt,</hi> &amp; thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke well of the motion, and take him home to houſe, and make <hi>much of him,</hi> when he were <hi>aged,</hi> and <hi>diſeaſed,</hi> and both vnfitt, and vnable, to doe buſines; ſurely noe; if he could not be <hi>broken,</hi> and brought to worke <hi>before,</hi> he should be <hi>beaten out</hi> now, though he did <hi>offer</hi> himſelf. And muſt God take that from <hi>vs,</hi> which <hi>we</hi> will not endure from <hi>beaſts?</hi> the <hi>laſt,</hi> the <hi>worſt,</hi> the <hi>dregs,</hi> and <hi>reffuſe</hi> of our dayes, muſt they fall to <hi>his share?</hi> the <hi>only vnfit time</hi> for any thing, muſt that be <hi>his only time,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> he shall have at our hands? Can we hope of acceptation and entertaynement in <hi>heaven,</hi> then, when, <hi>men</hi> refuſe, and the <hi>world</hi> refuſe's our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice?</p>
            <p>Wofull men, who hath bewitched you, that you should not beleeue the truth? Even <hi>Satan,</hi> who becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe he would have you wholy <hi>his owne,</hi> doth therefore witholde you from being Gods, till you be <hi>vnable</hi> to honour him, and it be <hi>impoſsible,</hi> he should receive you; it is <hi>he</hi> that doth abuſe you herin, he knowe's, it is with <hi>men</hi> in reſpect of <hi>God,</hi> as with <hi>beaſts</hi> in reſpect of <hi>men,</hi> in their aged dayes they are more fit for <hi>ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> then for <hi>ſervice,</hi> ſo <hi>olde men</hi> (who have deferred their duty) are <hi>now</hi> more like to be <hi>adjudged</hi> of God, for neglecting it in time <hi>past,</hi> then <hi>accepted</hi> for time to <hi>come.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20805:27"/>
            <p>What doth not every, thing weare, &amp; grow <hi>worſe</hi> with <hi>age?</hi> all <hi>olde</hi> things are accounted litle worth: <hi>olde</hi> cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes to put on; <hi>olde</hi> houſes to dwell in; &amp; the ſame we might ſay of all other things in their kinde, no man care's for, or regared's any ſuch. But this is <hi>wonderfull,</hi> that men who ſee, that the <hi>fruit of our ſin</hi> in other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures make's them vnſerviceable to <hi>vs,</hi> yee ſee not, <hi>ſin it ſelfe</hi> abiding, and encreaſing in vs, (for ſoe long ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me) should make vs <hi>ſoe</hi> to God. <hi>Time, vſe, age,</hi> doth corrupt all other things to vs, but <hi>ſin,</hi> (the only veny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and poyſon of all things) make's men (by this rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning) moſt <hi>fit</hi> for God, for the <hi>only time</hi> they chuſe <hi>for him</hi> is, when ſin hath had his greateſt <hi>ſway,</hi> all their lives before: as if the corruption of our nature, and life, had noe power at all, to <hi>enfeeble,</hi> or vnfit vs, for our God. Is not ſin our ſpirituall ſicknes, and the only <hi>deſperate diſeaſe</hi> of our whole man? hath it not <hi>a corroding</hi> quality, to eate <hi>quite through</hi> all the parts of our bodyes, all the <hi>powers</hi> of our ſoules, to pollute, infect, and annoy vs, in all reſpects? and who (I pray you) would entertayne, an <hi>aged, diſeaſed,</hi> and <hi>infected</hi> man into his houſe, as more fit for his turne <hi>now,</hi> then in his former times, when he was <hi>free</hi> from theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious maladies? thinke, (by your owne reaſon) <hi>what hart</hi> the Lord of heaven can have, to take in theſe <hi>late commers,</hi> being in farre <hi>worſe caſe,</hi> to ſerve him, then the <hi>most</hi> diſabled man, may be to attend a <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then, if we ſee reaſon to conceive, (as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but doe, if the Lord enlighten our eyes) that our wilfull, and wofull <hi>deferring</hi> of our duty till our <hi>olde</hi> dayes, doth deprive <hi>vs of harts</hi> to goe vnfaynedly to God, and debarre him from having <hi>a hart,</hi> graciouſly to accept of vs, then this <hi>plea</hi> is pernicious to vs, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20805:27"/>we (now we know it) moſt jmpious in vrging it, as we have done. But let vs come to the <hi>fourth</hi> &amp; laſt, plea, for this proroguation, of piety.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea. </seg>4</label> 4. It is pleaded, that there is mercy with God at any time, even at the <hi>last caſt,</hi> as the theife on the croſſe did well finde, and ſoe shall we, <hi>we hope,</hi> why should we not, even at our <hi>laſt</hi> breath.</p>
            <p>This pretence is put vpon vs <hi>daily;</hi> vpon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions we heare of it, at <hi>all times</hi> it is layd in our dish, to <hi>bolster</hi> vp rebellion againſt God, and to <hi>barre</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance vnto life. Noe <hi>word</hi> of God ſoe <hi>much</hi> abuſed, no <hi>worke</hi> of God <hi>more.</hi> This preſident of the Lords <hi>extraordinary</hi> mercy, is made the <hi>ordinary</hi> packhorſe to carry all mens jmpiety: and ſeing he was pleaſed to be ſoe gracious <hi>to one,</hi> he shall fare the worſe <hi>with many,</hi> for <hi>millious</hi> of men doe builde their <hi>graceleſſues,</hi> vpon this <hi>grace</hi> of his.</p>
            <p>But becauſe we finde by pitifull experience, that this <hi>holy</hi> worde, and this <hi>holy</hi> worke of God, (both being right worthy, to be thought vpon with all the admiration, and honor of our <hi>harts</hi>) is become the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>hackney</hi> wheron every <hi>hell-hounde</hi> rides poaſt, to his owne perdition; and as he goe's <hi>kicks</hi> and <hi>winces,</hi> at Gods long ſuffring, and loving kindnes: I will the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore endeavour the vttermoſt that I am albe, to ſee if <hi>ſome</hi> may yet be <hi>recalled,</hi> that are gone farre, and <hi>ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers</hi> may be <hi>stayed,</hi> that are comming after, and <hi>ſome preuented,</hi> that are ſetting out, to run this reprobate race.</p>
            <p>Vndoubtedly, did men deliberate at all, or could any <hi>wiſe conſideration</hi> enter into their ſoule's, they could not thus <hi>plead,</hi> they would not produce, this <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>matchleſſe</hi> example of favour and grace, to ſupport
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20805:28"/>their owne vngodly prophanes &amp; jmpiety. Yea, and to adde <hi>another</hi> evill to <hi>all</hi> the reſt, in the very vſe and vrging of it; to wit, to <hi>peruert,</hi> and abuſe the ſacred word of God, and to <hi>abaſe,</hi> and <hi>prostitute</hi> this glorious worke of his; either of <hi>which,</hi> whoſoever doth, he doeth it <hi>to his owne destruction,</hi> he deſtroye's himſelf in the very deede,
<note place="margin">2. Tet. 3.16. 2. Cor. 4. 3.4.</note> if the <hi>apoſtle</hi> ſay true in one place; and in another <hi>too,</hi> where he tell's vs, that <hi>if the Goſpell be hid</hi> (and ſoe it is to them, that <hi>can ſee</hi> to doe nothing with it, but to abuſe it) <hi>it is hid to them that are lost,</hi> who are hud winckt by the divell, that they diſcerne not the true ſence, &amp; vſe of the ſame, but vrge it, &amp; argue from it, to ſuch ends as God doth <hi>abhorre,</hi> that now his word muſt <hi>wounde</hi> himſelf, and nothing shall be made ſuch an occaſion of his <hi>dishonour,</hi> as that which he <hi>once</hi> did, to renowne himſelfe, and the <hi>glory</hi> of his goodnes,
<note place="margin">The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils of it</note> and favour for ever. And how doe we jmagine the Lord will take it, that his <hi>owne acts</hi> should be thus miſtaken, as to be made <hi>weapons</hi> againſt his owne <hi>majeſty,</hi> which he ordayned to deſtroy our <hi>jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety.</hi> Doubtleſſe, that theife, that malefactor, never did halfe the <hi>robbery,</hi> or any <hi>villany comparable</hi> to that which theſe men doe, who thus abuſe his example, to wrong the Lord, and their owne ſoules (and the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of others) ſoe vnſpeakeably as they doe. And that they may ſee and vnderſtand, (as they shall, if the Lord have a purpoſe to ſave them,) we will crave your patience and attention, to open in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler, the heavy and hydeous evills, that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted when this inſtance of Gods grace, is ſoe aledged.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill. </seg>1</label> 1. This is to make that <hi>common</hi> and <hi>ordinary,</hi> which God hath made <hi>peculiar,</hi> and <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20805:28"/>
            <p>Is it not thus? obſerve, and you shall ſee: what the Lord did at <hi>one time</hi> only and never <hi>before,</hi> nor <hi>ſince,</hi> (that we read off,) to <hi>one man</hi> only, &amp; not to any <hi>other</hi> but he, (for a <hi>ſecond example</hi> of ſuch favour is not to be found in all the revealed will of God;) and vpon a <hi>cauſe,</hi> and conſideration which shall never be ſeene againe, Chriſt being but <hi>once offred</hi> for vs. This doth every man vrge as his owne at <hi>all times,</hi> and in <hi>all caſes,</hi> without <hi>all</hi> conſideration of theſe perticulers before mentioned.</p>
            <p>Is not this to <hi>eclipſe,</hi> nay to <hi>cancell,</hi> the glory of the living God? and to caſt this moſt precious <hi>pearle</hi> befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all ſwyne, and trample this moſt <hi>holy thing</hi> vnder the feete of every prophane perſon, that the greateſt <hi>riches</hi> of his grace should be reached out to the veryeſt <hi>wretches</hi> in the world, who build nothing but <hi>contempt</hi> vpon this loving kindnes of the Lord? If it be ſuch a wofull thing to <hi>darken</hi> the <hi>counſell</hi> of God by words <hi>without</hi> knowledge (as it is ſayd in <hi>Iob?</hi>) muſt it not needes be a thing more damnable, to <hi>darken</hi> the <hi>kindnes</hi> of God, with words <hi>againſt</hi> knowledge, as theſe cannot but be, to every one of thoſe that <hi>thus</hi> abuſe them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> Againe what an <hi>abſurd, ſenſeleſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>ſinfull</hi> collection were <hi>this,</hi> or the like. <hi>Once, Balaams</hi> aſſe did ſpeake, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore <hi>every aſſe,</hi> should expect to doe the ſame. <hi>Once</hi> the <hi>ſea</hi> went back, and the water ſtood vpright as a <hi>wall</hi> on either hand to <hi>Iſraell,</hi> therefore every man might looke for the like paſſage: I thinke they that preſumed vpon it, and followed after them, found it not ſoe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Once,</hi> God ſent <hi>manna,</hi> and <hi>Quayles</hi> from heaven, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20805:29"/>
               <hi>water</hi> out of a rock, why should any man care to get meate or drinke, he may hope to have the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to feede him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Once, Naaman</hi> washed in Iorden and was cleane: <hi>On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> men were throwne into a <hi>fiery oven,</hi> and not burnt; <hi>Once,</hi> a <hi>bush</hi> did <hi>burne</hi> and <hi>not</hi> conſume; <hi>Once,</hi> Chriſt ſmote all his <hi>enemyes</hi> downe with a <hi>word</hi> or two. Why doe's not <hi>all</hi> the world depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon theſe perticulers, and reſolve to be releived in the <hi>ſame miſeryes,</hi> by the <hi>ſame meanes?</hi> It were a thing ſoone done, to deliver a multitude more of the like inſtances, wherin and from every of which, we might argue as warrantably, as from <hi>this</hi> of the <hi>theife.</hi> But the world is <hi>wiſe</hi> enough, not to be ſoe <hi>befooled,</hi> in theſe things that belong to the body, they can <hi>ſee,</hi> and <hi>ſay,</hi> theſe were all extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, &amp; miraculous &amp;, not to be looked for againe: And are ye not <hi>blinded</hi> by the prince of <hi>darknes</hi> (yee ſinfull ſoules) that yee should not <hi>more clearely ſee</hi> the ſame, in this that concern's ſoule and body too, and the eternall ſtate of both? <hi>Is</hi> there abſurdity in <hi>thoſe,</hi> &amp; ſence in <hi>this? doe</hi> thoſe inſtances ſeeme <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and may this ſeeme ſoe <hi>common?</hi> cannot you hope to have the benefit of <hi>thoſe,</hi> being miraculous, and muſt <hi>this</hi> be for all men, which is <hi>matchleſſe?</hi> Vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, either you muſt looke on them all <hi>alike,</hi> with a <hi>ſingle</hi> eye, and diſcerne them to be <hi>equally impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> or acknowledge that eye to be <hi>ſinfull,</hi> which can ſee <hi>odd's</hi> in things of the <hi>ſame</hi> kinde and nature, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, <hi>ſuch odd's</hi> as shall <hi>give</hi> God the honour of his favour and power in the <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>rob</hi> him of <hi>both,</hi> in the other.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>ſpectacles</hi> wherwith they thus ſee, are <hi>Satans,</hi> he make's them and putts them on and teache's them
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20805:29"/>to looke thus <hi>aſquint,</hi> on the things of God; If <hi>for</hi> foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, <hi>for</hi> phyſike; <hi>for</hi> paſſage over ſea, for victory over enemyes, or any ſuch things we should thus reaſon, the world would <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe</hi> at vs, as moſt <hi>witles</hi> fooles, nay our owne <hi>bellyes,</hi> our <hi>bodyes,</hi> our <hi>dangers,</hi> would teach vs to doe better, he muſt <hi>famish</hi> that gapes for <hi>quailes</hi> out of the cloudes, and he muſt <hi>perish</hi> that looke's for <hi>Naamans</hi> cure, &amp; he have his <hi>throat cut,</hi> that waites to have all his enemyes layd flat with a <hi>word: men</hi> will ſay there is no proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of reaſon in theſe things, &amp; the ſame doth the <hi>Lord</hi> (and the truth of his religion) ſay, in this inſtance, if thou hadſt an <hi>eare</hi> opened, a <hi>minde</hi> ſanctifyed, to heare and ſee it; as litle reaſon would appeare in <hi>this one,</hi> as <hi>in all the other,</hi> &amp; thou wouldſt as plainely ſee the jnevitable perdition of thy ſelf, in ſoule and body <hi>here,</hi> as in any of thoſe things named <hi>there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe but conſider well, whither this doe not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yle, &amp; vtterly make voyd, the verry <hi>marrow,</hi> and <hi>pith,</hi> the <hi>ſap,</hi> and <hi>juyce</hi> of Gods ſacred word, I meane the true <hi>application</hi> of the ſame, wherin conſiſteth the, <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>vertue,</hi> of all that God reveale's, and he that shall dare
<list>
                  <item>either to <hi>abridge</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>or, to <hi>enlarge</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>this,</hi> that it either fall <hi>short</hi> of Gods boundes, or doe <hi>exceede</hi> them, shall finde heavy (yet juſt) meaſure at Gods hands.</p>
            <p>The everlaſting <hi>rule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.15</note> and expreſſe <hi>canon</hi> of the ſcripture is this <hi>[That which God hath ſanctifyed, doe not then make common]</hi> this is Gods mynde; that things be <hi>not made</hi> otherwiſe then he <hi>meant</hi> them, that every thing be <hi>let</hi> alone, as he <hi>left</hi> it, and not once <hi>meddled</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:20805:30"/>withall, to any other ende. Who is he that shall now againſt the <hi>clearest</hi> light of knowledg and conſcience, <hi>violate,</hi> this abſolute law of the eternall God? But doth not every ſoule doe ſoe, that, vrge's <hi>this word</hi> of God, and ſuffers <hi>Satan</hi> to be his <hi>interpreter</hi> vpon it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his <hi>gloſſe,</hi> and embracing the divells <hi>commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> vpon Gods <hi>text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He it is, that make's this <hi>pearle,</hi> (even this <hi>peereleſſe,</hi> and <hi>priceleſſe</hi> pearle,) as ordinary as any <hi>pibble stone</hi> that lyes in the high way. I call it a <hi>pearle,</hi> and I acount it no leſſe then <hi>peereleſſe,</hi> becauſe it cannot be <hi>parale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> in any place, but was a <hi>preſident</hi> of wonderfull <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarity</hi> in all reſpects, as namely.
<list>
                  <item>to the <hi>party</hi> by whome.</item>
                  <item>to the <hi>partys</hi> before whome.</item>
                  <item>to the <hi>party</hi> to whome; it was done</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>first,</hi> to wit the <hi>party by whome,</hi> it was pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to Ieſus Chriſt, who was <hi>God,</hi> &amp; ſo could <hi>give gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> and <hi>forgive ſin,</hi> and <hi>convert</hi> a man in <hi>one moment,</hi> fully and extraordinarily: I thinke it would trouble the whole world, to finde an <hi>jufallible</hi> inſtance, that ever <hi>ordinary</hi> miniſter, or any <hi>meere man,</hi> hath done as much.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>ſecond,</hi> it was peculiar to the <hi>partyes before whome,</hi> that the adverſaryes, and excecutioners of the Lord Ieſus, might ſee the power of his <hi>diety</hi> shyning (at this time) through all the reproach, and miſery of his <hi>humanity:</hi> and ſoe be convinced (as ſome of them were) that he was the true <hi>meſsiah,</hi> and ſon of God, able to goe <hi>himſelf</hi> (at that time) to <hi>heaven,</hi> and carry <hi>anei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her</hi> with him, by the <hi>vertue</hi> that was in him.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>third,</hi> it was peculiar to the <hi>party to whome</hi> it was done, &amp; that in regard of his rare, and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20805:30"/>
               <hi>repentance,</hi> expreſſed in many particulers: the <hi>ſuddaine</hi> chang of his <hi>hart,</hi> and <hi>tongut</hi> (for <hi>he,</hi> as well as his <hi>fellow,</hi> did <hi>at first</hi> blaſpheme Chriſt) now he rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke's him, and condemnes both himſelfe and his fellow <hi>justly:</hi> the excellent <hi>confeſsion</hi> he made of Chriſt befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re them all, &amp; that <hi>now,</hi> when he was vpon the <hi>torture,</hi> where he could alſo, (not withſtanding <hi>all paynes</hi>) pray <hi>instantly;</hi> Did ever any barren dry <hi>tree,</hi> beare ſoe much fruit in an <hi>instant</hi> by any ordinary courſe? The fig tree was very ſtrangely and <hi>miraculouſly</hi> curſed, which <hi>ſo ſoone</hi> withered with a word of Chriſt mouth; and was not <hi>this tree</hi> miraculouſly bleſſed, which <hi>ſo ſoone</hi> did yeeld ſuch abundance? nay, was it not a greater, even a <hi>double miracle,</hi> that ſuch a <hi>bramble</hi> ſuch a <hi>rebell,</hi> should become an <hi>olive,</hi> and beare plentifully the firſt day, &amp; houre, of his being ſoe?</p>
            <p>Now then if all this be thus, that in each of theſe, and divers other inſtances, this particuler were ſoe <hi>peculiar,</hi> and <hi>extraordinary,</hi> what is it that any wicked man nay conclude <hi>hence</hi> for himſelf, more then <hi>this,</hi> (and <hi>note it well,</hi> thou godles, and graceleſſe perſon, as thou readeſt it.
<note place="margin">Note well.</note>) <hi>That when Ieſus Christ shall come againe in the flesh, and fall into the hands of men to be</hi> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed, <hi>and that</hi> two <hi>other must be</hi> hangd <hi>on either ſide of him, &amp; it come to</hi> thy turne <hi>to be</hi> one <hi>of thoſe</hi> two, <hi>&amp; the</hi> better <hi>of the</hi> twayne that hang's <hi>by him, vpon whome he will shew his</hi> diety <hi>to convert</hi> thee <hi>miraculouſly, &amp; vnto whome againe, thou sheweſt the fruits of repentance</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily, <hi>then, mayst</hi> thou <hi>be aſſured to ſpede as this</hi> theife <hi>did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other <hi>warrantize</hi> I can give none, vpon any other tearmes then <hi>theſe,</hi> in any <hi>common</hi> caſe: howſoever it is moſt true, that there want not <hi>evidences,</hi> nor <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:20805:31"/>at any ſuch time as the Lord shall pleaſe to excerciſe his ſpeciall patience, and grace; yet, by <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> of this example, or preſident, (every way <hi>thus</hi> extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary) no ſuch matter can be <hi>concluded,</hi> as moſt men would make of it: To delay what is due to the Lord, and to rejourne what he commands, hath no <hi>colour</hi> of ground or reaſon here, to doe ſoe is more then this <hi>theife</hi> himſelf did, who having (in all likelyhood) lived all his <hi>life</hi> without God, or any meanes of good, doth <hi>now</hi> come at the <hi>firſt</hi> call: which is more then <hi>thou</hi> haſt done, nay <hi>thou</hi> being daily called vpon, by the Lord, doeſt poaſt off thy comming to him, by <hi>his</hi> example, that came <hi>aſſoone</hi> as he was called: &amp; if thou doe <hi>worſe</hi> then he, doe'ſt hope to fare <hi>as well?</hi> nay rather, how righteouſly may the juſt God take <hi>this</hi> allegation out of thy mouth, and <hi>retort</hi> it vpon thee, who pleadeſt the putting off, of thy ſervice to the Lord, by his pretence, that made more then <hi>ordinary haſte</hi> to come to Ieſus Chriſt, and went <hi>ſo fast,</hi> towards him, that he got to heaven, <hi>the ſame day,</hi> with him.</p>
            <p>Beholde now wherevnto it is come, that every vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly man (that preſſe's this preſident to this purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe) is condemned out of his owne mouth, and the mouth of jniquity is <hi>stopped</hi> by <hi>that very evidence,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby it did <hi>open</hi> it ſelf againſt heaven. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> And this is the <hi>first</hi> of the miſcheifes that ariſeth from the miſaled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of this example, when men will ſoe <hi>vnreaſonably</hi> and without <hi>all ſence,</hi> preſſe, and plead, the <hi>last</hi> fruits of chriſts mercy to <hi>one</hi> malefactor, to prevent the <hi>first</hi> fruits of that duty, that all men owe to god their creator; and make that <hi>ordinary</hi> to <hi>every one,</hi> which he was pleaſed to jmpropriate but <hi>once,</hi> and but to <hi>one</hi> alone. and if they be ſoe <hi>deepe</hi> at the firſt <hi>step,</hi> let vs
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20805:31"/>looke a litle further how in going forward this way, they <hi>plunge</hi> thenſelves paſt all recovery into perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill </seg>2</label> 2. The <hi>perverſe;</hi> &amp; <hi>perverted</hi> preſſing of this <hi>thei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes</hi> particuler, to that end which vngodly men vrge it, doth breede moſt evident and jrrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable <hi>contradictions</hi> in the ſcriptures, &amp; <hi>make bate,</hi> betweene <hi>one</hi> part of Gods bleſſed word and <hi>another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he that doth thus, (if he did know what he doth) doubtleſſe, would looke well about him er'e he would offer it: For why? to ſet the ſcripture together by the eares, what is it? Is it not (as was obſerved befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re) to make God (who is truth it ſelf, and whoſe word it is) <hi>a lyar,</hi> for if one peice be contrary to another, all cannot be true and ſounde? Is it not to expoſe the ſacred booke of God to <hi>contempt,</hi> in taking from it that incommunicable property, and <hi>prerogative royall,</hi> that it hath aboue all bookes vnder heaven, to be ever more at abſolute <hi>vnity</hi> within it ſelf, and making it like humane writings which are full of <hi>error,</hi> and falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood? Is it not to make <hi>our preaching</hi> vayne, and <hi>your faith</hi> vayne, and to keepe you <hi>ſtill</hi> in your ſins? for if the <hi>ground</hi> wher vpon <hi>we</hi> preach, and you <hi>beleeve,</hi> be vnſounde, and not ſuch abſolute truth, as may beare vp <hi>both,</hi> then is <hi>neither</hi> to any purpoſe? Nay, is it not to bring all to vtter and remediles <hi>confuſion,</hi> by sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods foundation, and overthrowing the whole frame of his bleſſed building, vpon this infaillible truth of his owne, one <hi>title</hi> wherof, if it should be <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, noe worde</hi> of all the reſt, would be thought <hi>true,</hi> and foe <hi>theſe</hi> (like thoſe <hi>pagans</hi>) doe their beſt, to <hi>turne the truth of God into a lye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.26</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:20805:32"/>
            <p>Now is not the <hi>abuſiue</hi> vrging of this ſcripture, a ſetting of one word of God <hi>against</hi> another? let vs weigh it well, and we will <hi>ſee</hi> it, and <hi>ſay</hi> it alſo. For why? It is a ruled caſe, and paſt all queſtion, (as we have proved) that God will have the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of vs all, we have made Gods minde vndeniably manifeſt for <hi>that,</hi> now if that be <hi>ſoe,</hi> is not the allegation of this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as <hi>manifest</hi> a contradiction of this <hi>truth</hi> as may be; for why doe men ſtand vpon this ſcripture? why is it ſoe often vrged and itterated? why are we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed vpon, when we reprove mens jmpiety, and have this evermore caſt in our <hi>dish,</hi> from day to day? Is it not to plead for <hi>proroguation</hi> of piety till hearafter? do's it not make men ſay (through their owne jmpie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) that it is <hi>too ſoone</hi> yet? it is not <hi>yet time;</hi> there is <hi>time enough</hi> for theſe things in <hi>time to come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not <hi>theſe</hi> words made the only <hi>refuge</hi> of all <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions</hi> againſt God, and a <hi>counterpoyſon</hi> to that <hi>early,</hi> and <hi>timely</hi> duty, that we owe vnto him? doe not men thinke they have <hi>stop't</hi> our <hi>mouthes,</hi> and <hi>ſatiffyed</hi> their owne <hi>myndes</hi> ſufficiently, when they have <hi>thus</hi> ſpoken; and <hi>done</hi> enough, to <hi>vndoe</hi> all, that we can ſay to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And I pray you what call you this, but <hi>contradiction,</hi> when you oppoſe, &amp; ſet this <hi>one</hi> word of God, againſt <hi>all</hi> the words of God ſpoken elſwhere; when he ſoe often call's for the <hi>1. fruits,</hi> you will <hi>choake</hi> all, with that favour which was <hi>once</hi> shewed to one man, at the <hi>laſt?</hi> This is to <hi>confute</hi> one peice of ſcripture by anot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her: to overthrow Gods <hi>worde,</hi> by Gods <hi>worke,</hi> and ſoe to divide <hi>God</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Satan</hi> againſt <hi>Satan,</hi> to make the Lord <hi>ſay</hi> a thing, in one place, and in anot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her to <hi>vnſay</hi> it: and <hi>(finally)</hi> to draw from the Lord
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20805:32"/>himſelf a <hi>diſpenſation,</hi> and liberty of ſining, that ſoe what he requires in ſoe <hi>many</hi> places of his <hi>law,</hi> he shou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le releaſe, and cancell in <hi>one</hi> part of his <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let any man whome God hath endued with any meaſure of <hi>ſound</hi> vnderſtanding, judge whether this be not to make <hi>a rent in</hi> the Lords revealed wil; and if ſoe it be, it is time for vs <hi>to judg our ſelues,</hi> for ſoe doing, for before the Lord will endure this, the ſoule that doth it, shalbe <hi>rent</hi> from him, &amp; throwne among <hi>reprobates;</hi> the judgment and damnation of theſe <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracers</hi> of God, and <hi>depravers</hi> of his holy word, ſleepeth not; and there is noe way to shun, or eſcape it, but by a <hi>through</hi> judging of your ſelves, in reſpect of this impiety, which if they doe not, whoſe <hi>mouthes</hi> have ſpoken it, and whoſe <hi>myndes</hi> have thought it; venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance shall ſurely overtake them, even <hi>that vengeance,</hi> which is due to ſuch as doe this inſufferable <hi>indignity,</hi> to God, and his word.</p>
            <p>This is the 2. <hi>step</hi> they tread, who follow this way, &amp; we ſee it ſink's <hi>deeper</hi> then the former, toward that dreadfull confuſion which cannot be avoyed, if this fearfull evill be not abandoned. Let vs yet ſee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the <hi>third.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. the producing, and aleadging of this preſident of the theife <hi>thus,</hi> (that we may <hi>play the theiues</hi> with God, and <hi>rob him</hi> of his firſt fruits,) doth breede, and ingender many <hi>foule</hi> falshoods, and <hi>vile</hi> blaſphemyes in our harts.</p>
            <p>He that propoſeth this preſident for his <hi>apologie,</hi> againſt the manifeſt light of truth we have proved, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this ſcripture, the <hi>patrone</hi> of ſuch <hi>atheisticall</hi> principles as, are to be <hi>abhorred</hi> in the <hi>thought</hi> of every man, and not to be once <hi>vttered</hi> of any. Let vs ſee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20805:33"/>ſome <hi>few</hi> of thoſe <hi>many</hi> monſtrous vntruths which we might mention.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill, </seg>3</label> 1. it doth poſeſſe vs with a perſwaſion that by <hi>authority</hi> of ſcripture, we may rejourne the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience that <hi>long ſince</hi> we owed vnto the Lord.</p>
            <p>Wheras the holy ghoſt is clearely oppoſite here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: God calleth for nothing <hi>more,</hi> (as we have heard) then the <hi>first,</hi> and condemneth nothing more then putting off what he command's. His ſervants, (ſuch as he hath <hi>effectually</hi> called) have made all the haſte and expedition that was poſſible: So ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> [I <hi>will run the way of thy commandements</hi>] and againe <hi>[I made haste and delayed not to keepe thy righteous judgments]</hi> So ſaith <hi>Cornelius</hi> to <hi>Peter [Then I ſent for thee jmmediately]</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith the ſame of himſelf <hi>[jmme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately I conſulted not with flesh and blood &amp;c.]</hi> The evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.32.60. Act. 10.33. Gal. 1.16.</note> to haſten our duty is <hi>vndeniable:</hi> the ſin of not doing ſoe, is <hi>in excuſable:</hi> yet by <hi>theſe</hi> mens argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the ſame God that is ſoe eager for <hi>expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> doth warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our <hi>delay.</hi> And can any thing be more falſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that God should abet <hi>theſe</hi> two contraries.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill, </seg>4</label> 2. it doth patronage not only <hi>delay,</hi> but <hi>preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous</hi> delay, ſuch, as men are guilty of by preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>(against all good ground)</hi> they shall finde the ſame meaſure of mercy that this <hi>theife</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Now to preſume of pardon for a ſin of <hi>preſumption,</hi> is to preſume of more favour then the <hi>theife</hi> found, for, (for ought we know) his ſin was not of preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but either of <hi>meere ignorance</hi> if he were a <hi>Romane,</hi> (as ſome ſuppoſe <hi>him</hi> &amp; his <hi>fellow,</hi> to bee) or of <hi>groſſe ignorance</hi> if he were a <hi>Iew.</hi> Sure it is, he knew not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for he <hi>reviled</hi> him at the firſt, as well as the other. And muſt you (by his example) preſume of delay in Gods dutyes, which he never <hi>meant,</hi> and of mercy for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20805:33"/>delay which this <hi>theife</hi> never <hi>found?</hi> shall God become the <hi>prop</hi> of our preſumtion, when it is a ſin that his ſoule hate's, and he is ſoe farre from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any mercy in <hi>ſtore</hi> for it, that he hath not greater <hi>store</hi> of juſtice heaped vp, ſcarce againſt <hi>any</hi> vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; &amp; they that <hi>befaulty</hi> are ſayd to <hi>ſtore, or treaſure vp wrath, against the day of wrath,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">Ro. 2.5.</note> every day to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, enlarge, and adde vnto their owne damnation.</p>
            <p>This jmpiety is <hi>next neighbour</hi> to that which is <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable,</hi> if once a man be ſoe jmpudent that he da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res offend <hi>preſumptuouſly,</hi> he had neede bethinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf where <hi>he is,</hi> and what <hi>he doe's,</hi> the next <hi>leape</hi> may be into the bottomleſſe pit, eſpecially if he shall adde <hi>this</hi> vnto all, that he will <hi>father</hi> ſuch offences vpon the Lords allowance, &amp; ſoe turne his extraordinary <hi>mercy,</hi> into extraordinary <hi>jmpiety. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>
                  </label> David</hi> had another ſpirit when he prayed againſt preſumptuous ſin, that he might be free from <hi>the great tranſgreſsion;</hi> &amp; did not the ſpirit of the divell poſeſſe theſe wofull men,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 19.13</note> they would ſurely doe the ſame. But <hi>Satan</hi> ha's <hi>enough,</hi> even <hi>all</hi> that he would have, to make them <hi>build</hi> their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption vpon God, becauſe he knowe's that by <hi>ſoe</hi> doing, he shall provoke God againſt them, to abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re them for ever. But let vs looke yet a litle further.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Evill </seg>5</label> 3. The vrging of this example <hi>thus,</hi> doth <hi>looſe vs,</hi> &amp; <hi>bynde God,</hi> we are <hi>enlarged</hi> for all our life till the <hi>laſt,</hi> his hands are <hi>tyed,</hi> &amp; that with <hi>double bands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not this vndeniably true, and a cleare conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of this allegation? doe we not preſſe it to put off that wherevnto we are <hi>bound, not</hi> to give the Lord <hi>first</hi> of our lives, <hi>but</hi> to be <hi>free</hi> to come when we will, though at the laſt <hi>day,</hi> or <hi>houre,</hi> or <hi>instant?</hi> doe we not take it for graunted, that till we doe come, we muſt have <hi>health, peace, foode,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:20805:34"/>and all other <hi>favours</hi> from God? and that we muſt be accepted alſo?</p>
            <p>So we are <hi>free,</hi> God is <hi>bound:</hi> we are free from <hi>duty</hi> during our pleaſure (and a great deale of <hi>kindnes we must have</hi> for many yeares, and doe him no <hi>ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi>) but he is <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>mayntaine</hi> vs <hi>till</hi> we come, and <hi>entertayne</hi> vs <hi>when</hi> we come. And is it not fearfull and hydeous jmpiety, for vs to ſeeke to <hi>enſlave</hi> the Lord to our ſinfull lives, and to ſet our ſelves at <hi>liberty</hi> in them againſt <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps you will ſay, God hath bound himſelf ſaying. <hi>[At what time ſoever a ſinner shall repent him]</hi> and that Chriſt hath done the ſame ſaying <hi>[he that commeth to me I cast not away].</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, if (touching the former) we graunt the truth of thoſe words (though they are not <hi>litterally</hi> expreſſed in any text) that the Lord will refuſe none, but is tyed to take them when they come, yet I hope it is with <hi>condition,</hi> of their comming as they <hi>ought</hi> to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; that is, with warrant from him, at his <hi>call:</hi> with <hi>abilitye</hi> of grace from him to repent: without <hi>both</hi> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, it is an jmpoſſibility to come; and if we come not <hi>thus,</hi> (as we are bounde to doe) God is <hi>free to refuſe vs.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> Now they that have refuſed to come at his call in their <hi>younge</hi> yeares, may feare whether they shalbe called in their <hi>olde</hi> dayes, and neglecting grace ſo <hi>long;</hi> how can they hope to have it at ſuch <hi>short</hi> warning as a litle before death, or, (as the moſt of them ſay) at the <hi>last gaſpe?</hi> and without <hi>theſe</hi> they cannot come.</p>
            <p>If the word <hi>[whenſoever,]</hi> or, <hi>[at what time ſoever &amp;c.]</hi> Were in the text, I hope it muſt be vnderſtood of <hi>Gods time,</hi> not of <hi>ours;</hi> it muſt be one of <hi>his [whens]</hi> not of <hi>ours;</hi> we muſt not be <hi>chuſers</hi> to tye <hi>him</hi> to our
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20805:34"/>
               <hi>time;</hi> noe, he is our <hi>commander</hi> and may binde vs to <hi>his:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> now all <hi>[whenſoevers]</hi> or <hi>[what times ſoever]</hi> are not the <hi>times</hi> that he calleth to repentance, for (beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des what we ſayd before) that they cannot hope of any time to be called, who have refuſed the time wherin they were called: we finde in the <hi>parable,</hi> that after the <hi>eleaventh houre,</hi> God ſent not out to call any, it being a time <hi>too late,</hi> to <hi>begin;</hi> &amp; <hi>too short,</hi> to <hi>ende,</hi> any buſines of <hi>his,</hi> shewing that our laſt houre is noe time for vs to <hi>goe</hi> to God, or for God to <hi>regard</hi> vs.</p>
            <p>The ſame is the ſence of the latter, which Chriſt ſaith: ſoe that God is bound to vs in <hi>kindnes,</hi> when we have performed our part of <hi>obedience.</hi> Doe your <hi>duty,</hi> you shall finde <hi>mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> Doe not make ſuch <hi>wylde</hi> and vnlimmited propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, vnderſtand what God ſaith with all reverence, wiſdome, and <hi>ſobriety,</hi> know, that every word of his flowe's from infinite and vnſearcheable <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and therefore muſt be conceived <hi>warily,</hi> as doctrine of <hi>piety,</hi> not of <hi>liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beware of <hi>bynding</hi> God, and <hi>looſeing</hi> thy felf, leaſt (for ſoe doing) he bynde thee hand and feete, and caſt thee into vtter darknes: doe not once dare to thinke that <hi>he</hi> that is <hi>only wiſe,</hi> could ever be ſoe <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,</hi> as to reveale, or write any <hi>one</hi> word, that might j<hi>mbaſe</hi> himſelf, and give vs any occaſion to <hi>abuſe</hi> him, as in <hi>thus</hi> diſputing from theſe propoſitions we doe.</p>
            <p>Nay, we are <hi>bound,</hi> and he is <hi>free,</hi> it was his <hi>free grace,</hi> to make any ſuch promiſes of grace, or glory to vs, vpon any tearmes, ſeing <hi>we</hi> brake with him and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt him at the <hi>firſt,</hi> he might have choſen whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever he would have given vs <hi>one good word</hi> or noe; now ſeing he hath, let that be acknowledged as his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20805:35"/>love, and let vs confeſſe our ſelves <hi>bound</hi> to every titt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of his truth, that doth or may concerne vs, and give our <hi>beſt obedience</hi> we can to the ſame with joy, grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving allwayes that we can give <hi>no better.</hi> Be it farre from vs thus to <hi>captivate</hi> the Lord, ſoe much as in <hi>one</hi> thought it is abhominable, it is for malefactors (ſuch as we are) to be <hi>bounde,</hi> not for him who is God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to be bleſſed for ever. And be it as farre from vs to <hi>free our ſelves,</hi> but allwayes to confeſſe our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Lord with all humility, yea to accomt it our <hi>best liberty</hi> to be bounde to him, whoſe law is abſolute <hi>liberty.</hi> The ſervice of <hi>Satan</hi> is the <hi>baſest bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> that can be, and to be (by him) witholden from God (as we are) till the <hi>last</hi> of our lives, is abſolute <hi>ſlavery,</hi> and that whereby he meane's <hi>indeede</hi> (what ſoever he <hi>pretend's</hi> to delude vs) to pull vs into his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne chaynes, to be bound vp with himſelf for ever, for refuſing to come vnder Gods yoake, when he did call vs.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee in theſe few ſteps, how <hi>farre</hi> from <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> how <hi>neere</hi> to <hi>hell</hi> theſe men goe, that make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to make but <hi>one leape</hi> from earth to heaven, and that at <hi>laſt caſt</hi> too; if we should follow them further, in ſuch other moſt blaſphemous and curſed conſequences, as would as well <hi>flow</hi> from this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as they aledge it) as any of thoſe we have <hi>noted,</hi> &amp; refuted; we might goe with them to <hi>hell gates,</hi> and ſee them <hi>shut in,</hi> to the reſt of their fellowes, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve lived and dyed in the <hi>abuſe</hi> of this <hi>word,</hi> and <hi>worke</hi> of God, becauſe their, harts &amp; lives, were <hi>shut</hi> againſt God, &amp; they would not <hi>open</hi> to him, when he knockt <hi>ſeaſonably</hi> to their ſalvation, but depended vpon the <hi>mercy</hi> shewed to this <hi>theife,</hi> without any conſideration
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20805:35"/>of theſe <hi>other</hi> things that are thervnto appertayning, noe the divell will not have them once dreame.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Either of the <hi>extraordinary occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> of his converſion, which was to expreſſe the <hi>power,</hi> &amp; <hi>honor</hi> of Chriſts <hi>diety,</hi> even <hi>now,</hi> in the time of his greateſt <hi>abaſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Or, of the <hi>extraordinary meanes</hi> of his converſion, which was <hi>Christ himſelf,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Or, of the <hi>extraordinary manner</hi> of his converſion, which was in a <hi>ſmall time,</hi> on the <hi>gallowes,</hi> or <hi>gibbett,</hi> or <hi>croſſe;</hi> call it as you will.</item>
               <item>Or of the <hi>extraordinary manifestation</hi> of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by the <hi>honour</hi> he gave to Chriſt, the <hi>shame</hi> he tooke to himſelf, before all Chriſtes enemyes, and his owne, &amp; that effectuall <hi>prayer</hi> of faith, whereto he had ſoe <hi>ſweete an anſwer.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe things and the like, shall not <hi>once</hi> enter into the jmaginations of theſe men; they only remember he found <hi>mercy,</hi> without any further thought of any of the aforeſayd particulers, that reſpected either <hi>what</hi> Chriſt did, or why; or <hi>what</hi> he did; no, <hi>Satan</hi> hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de's theſe matters from them, leaſt they should (ſeing ſoe many <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>deedes too,</hi> went to this bargaine) bethinke themſelves better of it, and not <hi>rest</hi> in ſuch a ſlight conceit of the matter as they have done. This preſident, the divell make's his pretended <hi>pick-locke</hi> to open heaven to all theſe that he can thus delude: but it proves <hi>intruth,</hi> his <hi>pitfall</hi> by which, millious of men tumble into hell, in that <hi>laſt moment</hi> of time, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein all their life before, they made full account to goe to heaven: &amp; ſoe before they are <hi>a ware,</hi> the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomeleſſe pit hath ſwallowed them vp, &amp; there they lye <hi>howling</hi> in endles, &amp; eaſeleſſe miſery, who thought <hi>verily,</hi> to have bene with this theife in <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:20805:36"/>
            <p>Noe, noe, his <hi>conveyance</hi> was every way, and in all reſpects <hi>extraordinary,</hi> his paſſage is jmpoſſible (for ought we know) to any other; eſpecially for <hi>thoſe</hi> who would goe the ſame <hi>way,</hi> and yet regard not at all the <hi>way</hi> he went.</p>
            <p>Thus we have waded through ſome <hi>few,</hi> of thoſe <hi>many</hi> things, which, are ordinarily alledged to hinder the happy ſucceſſe of this ſacred truth of God in mens harts, and their happines by the obedience and practiſe of it. We will now goe no further in this way, the further we paſſe the <hi>fowler</hi> it will appeare, and our hope is that ſuch as are not gone <hi>too farre,</hi> but are yet within <hi>call,</hi> may be recalled, by this voyce of God, which hath tolde them the <hi>danger</hi> of every <hi>step</hi> they have gone as yet, &amp; the <hi>damnation</hi> that they will run into, if they (ſtill goe on) &amp; returne not, in due time, to ſave themſelves, from the wrath to come, which is reſerved for all <hi>ſuch,</hi> as reſiſt Gods revealed will, and labour to defend their <hi>protraction</hi> of duty, and their <hi>practiſe</hi> of jmpiety, by ſuch plea's and pretences, as come from that hell <hi>originally,</hi> whervnto, (they that perſiſt in them) muſt goe <hi>eternally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to preſerve ſoe many of them as is poſſible; now they have <hi>done</hi> pleading for ſin, (againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God and the good of their owne ſoules) we will <hi>begin</hi> to plead both for <hi>God,</hi> and for <hi>them,</hi> and the happines they may have by this bleſſed truth of <hi>his,</hi> if they have ſuch harts as may yet be mooved &amp; perſwaded to embrace the ſame.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> To which end, we now come to our <hi>third</hi> vſe, wherin we shall make tender vnto them of ſuch <hi>motiues,</hi> and <hi>conſiderations,</hi> as may jnduce any <hi>hart,</hi> (that is not wholy <hi>hardened</hi> and ſealed vp, or ſeared by <hi>Satan,</hi> to a <hi>ſtarke</hi> ſencleſſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20805:36"/>condition), to yeeld both acknowledgment &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to that which (in this behalfe) the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of them.</p>
            <p>The thing the Lord expecteth, is the <hi>first</hi> fruits of our liues to be <hi>his,</hi> that aſſoone as we can <hi>vndertake</hi> any thing, we should <hi>betake</hi> our ſelves to his ſervice; and can we conceit he doth this without right, or reaſon? Farre be ſuch jmpious jmmaginations from our harts. Let vs pervſe <hi>ſeriouſly,</hi> ſome <hi>few</hi> particulers that may be <hi>powerfull,</hi> and <hi>perſwaaing</hi> with vs herein. And firſt we will begin with thoſe grounds whervpon <hi>legally,</hi> the Lord required them, which if we ponder, and paralell according to their <hi>morall,</hi> we shall ſee enough to moue men, to doe as God would have them: Note then, that the <hi>firſt</hi> fruits were to be given to theſe <hi>enſuing</hi> ends,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Lord might be honoured in this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and power, wherby he gave <hi>Iſarell</hi> that goodly land, by giving him <hi>his right</hi> in the <hi>firſt</hi> of every thing.</p>
            <p>The <hi>first</hi> of all was the Lords <hi>right,</hi> and appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to himſelf, by his owne ordinance and decree: he that gave it not, <hi>rob'd</hi> God of his <hi>due,</hi> and was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the higeſt <hi>ſacriledge</hi> that could be committed.</p>
            <p>Yea, the Lord was ſoe abſolute herein, that all the <hi>first</hi> should be entyre to himſelf, that if it were not given <hi>him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.20.</note> yet they might not reſerve it to their <hi>owne</hi> vſe, as is evident in that inſtance of the <hi>aſſe,</hi> which being an vncleane beaſt, it was to be redeemed by <hi>a lambe,</hi> but if the owner <hi>aid</hi> not redeeme it, he might not let it live; but <hi>must breake the neck of it].</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then, who ſeeth not through this <hi>shaddow,</hi> that our <hi>first</hi> time is the Lords abſolute right, and that we
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20805:37"/>are <hi>theiues</hi> to our God, if we giue not our ſelves to him, and this <hi>fellony</hi> we may not jmagine to be eaſily anſwered; it is no ſlight matter to be falſe to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, to be a <hi>robber</hi> of the moſt high, it is not our <hi>booke</hi> will ſave vs, yet <hi>his booke</hi> (if we wilbe ruled by it) will shew vs the meanes how to be <hi>ſaved.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of being a <hi>theife</hi> and a <hi>robber</hi> is great, but the punishment is greater, he that repent's not ſincerely of it, will aſſuredly rue it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God will have the <hi>firſt</hi> from vs, that we might have <hi>right</hi> to the reſt from him.</p>
            <p>Till he have <hi>his,</hi> nothing of all we have is <hi>ours,</hi> when we have given him his right in the <hi>first,</hi> then, (and not till then) he gives vs right to the <hi>rest,</hi> and this is as plaine as the former, in the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the places forealedged,</p>
            <p>Wherin as we ſee the great &amp; moſt gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, in providing and caering for <hi>our interest,</hi> that what we have, we might holde it from him in a lawfull and comfortable <hi>tenure.</hi> Soe the greater and more heavy is the <hi>morall</hi> and meaning of this heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truth to them, who denying the Lord his right, doe thereby ſpoyle their <hi>owne,</hi> &amp; by the jmpious neglect of giving the Lord <hi>his,</hi> doe proclaime to all men that nothing they have is <hi>theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every vngodly man that honours not the Lord with his <hi>first,</hi> is a theife and a vſurper of all he doth poſeſſe, and lives vnder the juſt reproach of a <hi>fellon</hi> before God, and in the danger of that juſtice due to this offence, he is in perpetuall perill, every moment, &amp; hath <hi>heavens indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> hanging over his head, ready at all times to be <hi>arrested, arraigned, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned</hi> &amp; <hi>excecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by the high poſeſſor of heaven &amp; earth, the great
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20805:37"/>
               <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>owner</hi> of all that every man hath, who give's no man title to any thing he hath, vnleſſe he himſelfe <hi>firſt</hi> have his due.</p>
            <p>A wicked mans foode, rayment, riches, his whole eſtate is <hi>ſtolen goods,</hi> whereſoever he <hi>goe's,</hi> whatſoever he <hi>doe's,</hi> how long, or litle ſoe ever he live's, every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of his life is perilous, and may prove the very moment of his eternall death; his life is not his <hi>owne,</hi> himſelf is not his <hi>owne,</hi> he hath no right to the breath he drawe's, to the earth he treads on, to any thing appertayning to his being: all is <hi>for feit</hi> to the Lord of all, for <hi>none-payment</hi> of theſe <hi>first</hi> fruits.</p>
            <p>And herof may we be well aſſured; if we well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the Lord would not be ſoe <hi>vnwiſe,</hi> as to gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve vs any thing to ſerve <hi>Satan</hi> withall, noe, he ever gave vs, that we might enjoy it to <hi>his</hi> honour, and to our <hi>owne</hi> advantage. Now if he pleaſe to give vs harts to give him the <hi>firſt,</hi> he will graciouſly continue the ſame hart in vs, to give him the <hi>reſt</hi> alſo: wheras if <hi>Satan</hi> ſet in <hi>firſt,</hi> it is great wonder if he have not the <hi>laſt</hi> too, for he vſeth to holde hard for that which he <hi>once</hi> hath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. the Lord will have the <hi>firſt,</hi> that the reſt may be not only <hi>ours,</hi> but <hi>ſanctifyed</hi> to vs alſo, that the <hi>right</hi> we have in it, and the <hi>vſe</hi> we have of it, may both be ſeaſoned and ſweetened to vs, when we have <hi>firſt</hi> given God that which is Gods.</p>
            <p>And without a vſe <hi>ſanctifyed</hi> what is, or can any thing be to vs? <hi>Beaſts,</hi> that want reaſon have a naturall vſe of earthly comforts: <hi>Pagans,</hi> that want <hi>religion</hi> have a <hi>civill</hi> vſe of that which they have, now there is no difference betweene their <hi>tenure</hi> and ours,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20805:38"/>but this (wherin we exceede them) that we have both the <hi>naturall,</hi> and <hi>civill,</hi> ſanctifyed vnto vs. It is <hi>theirs</hi> in that ſtate wherin ſin left it, with the whole curſe of ſin vpon it: It is <hi>ours</hi> as Chriſt Ieſus hath pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed it and made it <hi>holy</hi> to vs. So all is <hi>poyſoned</hi> to him that is in Gods <hi>debt</hi> for this due: and to him that hath diſcharged it (to his beſt ability) all is <hi>bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[<hi>If the first fruits be holy</hi> (ſaith the apoſtle) <hi>ſoe is the lumpe</hi>] if they be not,
<note place="margin">Ro. 11.16</note> the lumpe cannot be. Tye the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe <hi>two</hi> motives together, and ſee how ſtrong they are to binde vs to the obedience of this inſtruction; if we have <hi>no right</hi> at all, then we <hi>steale</hi> all we have, if no <hi>ſanctifyed vſe,</hi> all we <hi>ſteale</hi> is envenomed to vs, ſoe that <hi>firſt,</hi> we are theives to God in <hi>vſing</hi> what we have <hi>no right</hi> in, and next, we are <hi>murderers</hi> of our ſelves, in the <hi>vnſanctifyed</hi> eſtate of that we vſe. Now what migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vnmatchable miſery is it for a man, to live by <hi>stealing</hi> all he <hi>eate's,</hi> and to <hi>dye in eating,</hi> all he <hi>ſteale's,</hi> Let vs thinke on theſe motives, which are the <hi>ſubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> of thoſe jnducements, which the ceremoniall law did but <hi>shaddow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We now proceede to preſſe a few other, which may yet <hi>more</hi> move vs, if we ponder them as we ought: either in the <hi>benefit,</hi> that come's by the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of this truth, or the <hi>evill</hi> that iſſue's from the neglect thereof. I pray you note <hi>bath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, if we did give the Lord our <hi>firſt,</hi> doe but thinke what a world of <hi>ſin</hi> we might <hi>ſave,</hi> which is committed and continued in, by <hi>millions</hi> till we doe give our ſelves to God.</p>
            <p>Did we throughly know the danger of <hi>one</hi> ſin (even the <hi>leaſt</hi> we can be guilty of,) we would doe much to prevent it, ſeing that, everlaſting pordition is <hi>due</hi> to it,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20805:38"/>but here is a courſe that would ſpare a multitude, nay <hi>all</hi> our trangreſſions, for from the time we are the Lords, he reckon's <hi>no ſin</hi> to vs, but account's vs <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> and accept's vs <hi>blameleſſe</hi> in his beloved.</p>
            <p>Now to avoyd ſin, with the <hi>dishonor</hi> it brings to God, with the <hi>damnation</hi> it brings to vs, (yea, &amp; to others too, by our example,) who would not re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the Lord his <hi>right,</hi> &amp; moſt freely let him have his <hi>owne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs,</hi> that <hi>Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> might never have <hi>us</hi> as his owne <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God.</hi> Aſſuredly he that coulde ever conceive the Lords <hi>damage,</hi> &amp; his owne <hi>diſadvantage,</hi> by ſin: what <hi>glory</hi> God wants, what <hi>greife</hi> it is to his ſpirit, what <hi>provocation</hi> it is to his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, how <hi>jniurious</hi> to his goodnes and favour, how <hi>abuſiue</hi> to his long ſuffering &amp; loving kindenes; would never deny himſelf to the Lord from the <hi>firſt day</hi> he did vnderſtand, how he might <hi>(acceptablely)</hi> yeeld him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf vnto him, what a <hi>ſiranger</hi> should <hi>Satan</hi> be in vs? what a <hi>familiar</hi> would God be to vs? if we begin beti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes with him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider that as we might <hi>ſave</hi> much <hi>ſin,</hi> ſoe this were alſo the only way, to <hi>have</hi> much <hi>grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The more <hi>early</hi> any thing begins to be <hi>good,</hi> the more <hi>goodnes</hi> is hoped from it: the <hi>ſooner</hi> any man ſett's himſelf towards <hi>beaven,</hi> the <hi>more heavenly</hi> muſt he needes be. Oh, what a moſt happy thing is it, when <hi>grace</hi> begins to grow <hi>betimes</hi> in vs; <hi>then</hi> is the <hi>Lord</hi> much <hi>honoured</hi> by vs, <hi>then</hi> are <hi>men</hi> much <hi>bettered</hi> by vs, then are we <hi>fitter</hi> for all duty; then are we more <hi>ſafe</hi> from <hi>ſin,</hi> &amp; the <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagion</hi> of <hi>ſinners;</hi> then are we mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re able to <hi>worke out</hi> our ſalvation; and <hi>more ſure</hi> to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the ſame. A mans life is a <hi>heaven</hi> vpon <hi>earth,</hi> when his graces are <hi>well growne</hi> in him, <hi>his</hi> affection, <hi>his</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation cannot but be in <hi>heaven:</hi> ſuch a man may
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20805:39"/>be <hi>bolde</hi> with his God at all times, and <hi>Satan</hi> can have no hope to prevaile againſt <hi>him,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it cometh ſoe to paſſe with a man in <hi>good,</hi> as it did with him in <hi>evill,</hi> in whome the divell had beene <hi>from a childe,</hi> he was the more <hi>hardly</hi> caſt out, &amp; ſoe the more <hi>eaſily</hi> is he kept out, and <hi>hardly,</hi> (nay never shall he poſſibly enter) to poſeſſe that perſon, who <hi>of a childe</hi> and from the <hi>firſt</hi> hath beene gracious.</p>
            <p>What have we in this worlde <hi>to doe,</hi> or to buſy our ſelves <hi>moſt</hi> about, but to get <hi>that grace</hi> that may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vs to glory: and what better way to get <hi>much,</hi> then to fall to worke, <hi>aſſoone</hi> as is poſſible?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider, that the Lord never gave any man <hi>a time of grace,</hi> that would dare to <hi>ſet</hi> God a time to <hi>come for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The man that shalbe ſoe jmpious, and <hi>jmpudent;</hi> as to <hi>preſcribe</hi> and <hi>lymit</hi> the Lord, at what time he will come, never hath hart to come <hi>at all.</hi> Is it not good reaſon that when we <hi>neglect,</hi> (yea and <hi>deſpiſe</hi> too) ſo great ſalvation, as is <hi>tendered,</hi> nay <hi>commanded</hi> to vs, in our <hi>tender</hi> yeares, that <hi>he</hi> whome we have denyed in <hi>his time</hi> of grace, should deny vs in our <hi>time of ſin?</hi> eſpecially conſidering that he hath power, to <hi>confine vs,</hi> to the inſtant of <hi>his call;</hi> but it is <hi>intollerable</hi> jmpiety in vs, to <hi>bounde him to ours.</hi> Shall <hi>God</hi> waite vpon the <hi>diuell,</hi> and accept vs at that <hi>houre,</hi> when our <hi>ſin</hi> will let vs come, we having caſt of <hi>his</hi> day, &amp; houre, of <hi>mercy</hi> before?</p>
            <p>How reade we in the ſcriptures for <hi>this,</hi> what finde we? nothing but <hi>thunder</hi> and <hi>lightening,</hi> from heaven, to <hi>peale</hi> theſe wicked wretches to <hi>perdition, [They that were bidae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were not worthy]</hi> ſaith Chriſt. And againe [<hi>The dore was shut]</hi> againſt them that were not prepared
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20805:39"/>
               <hi>for</hi> the bridegrome, at <hi>the instant</hi> of his comming, and though (at their <hi>owne time</hi>) they came (afterwarde) with much <hi>jntreaty,</hi> yet, it could not be opened, but they were banished <hi>thence,</hi> and abandoned to <hi>hell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pre. 1.24.25.26. Zach. 7.13.</note> And yet <hi>againe,</hi> by the prophets: <hi>[Becauſe I have called and you have refuſed, therefore shall yee cry and not be heard]</hi> So that (you ſee) God ſett's <hi>noe</hi> time to him, that ſetts God <hi>any;</hi> nothing remayne's to <hi>ſuch,</hi> but <hi>diſdayne</hi> from heaven, <hi>damnation</hi> in hell.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider, that what extraordinary honour God ever intended to himſelf, by any <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>men,</hi> whome he would make <hi>instruments</hi> of the ſame, he meant to make all ſuch <hi>perſons</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>betime.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe but ponder it well in the <hi>first Adam,</hi> &amp; in the <hi>ſecond,</hi> In the <hi>firſt,</hi> all <hi>mankinde</hi> might have beene hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and God <hi>mightily</hi> honoured through all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; now to bring this about, <hi>Adam</hi> shalbe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous from his <hi>first being,</hi> and honour the Lord from the <hi>time</hi> of his <hi>creation.</hi> In the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> all the <hi>elect</hi> shalbe happy, &amp; (through him) the glory of Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite favour, shall shyne vpon <hi>them;</hi> &amp; to furnish <hi>him</hi> for this <hi>wonderfull</hi> worke, he ſanctifyed himſelf <hi>befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> he was <hi>borne,</hi> and (after) in our <hi>infancy,</hi> and (ſoe) throughout <hi>all ages</hi> of our life, during the dayes he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Indeede, he attayned not our <hi>olde age</hi> (I will not take vpon me <hi>peremptorily</hi> to determine <hi>why;</hi> but) it may be it was to shew, that <hi>olde age</hi> doth not <hi>eaſily</hi> attayne <hi>him;</hi> that ſoe theſe preſumptuous, <hi>olde fooles,</hi> might be the more <hi>terrefyed,</hi> and <hi>daunted,</hi> from dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be ſo <hi>audacious,</hi> as they have beene.</p>
            <p>Did the Lord ever <hi>glorify</hi> himſelf in that man, or <hi>glorify</hi> that man with himſelf, that (refuſing to come
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20805:40"/>when God <hi>called</hi>) came when himſelf <hi>would?</hi> name <hi>one</hi> inſtance if it be poſſible, Noe, he will ſanctify <hi>all ſuch,</hi> as shalbe glorious <hi>to him</hi> in earth, or glorious <hi>with him</hi> in heaven, I ſay he will ſanctify <hi>all ſuch,</hi> in his <hi>purpoſe</hi> before time, and in his <hi>practiſe,</hi> in ſuch time, as wherin they shall <hi>come</hi> when he shall <hi>call,</hi> be it more <hi>early,</hi> as <hi>Ieremiah: Ioſiah; John Baptist:</hi> or more <hi>late,</hi> as <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſuch other, as we have named before. He gave them harts to attend <hi>his</hi> time, not <hi>one</hi> of them ever dared to reject <hi>that,</hi> and to cauſe the Lord to attend <hi>theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe few <hi>inducements</hi> I hope shall draw, and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce vs to the Lord, <hi>whoſe</hi> we are, and <hi>whoſe</hi> all our dayes are, and all our <hi>abilityes</hi> both of body and ſoule; <hi>from him</hi> we have them in <hi>mercy,</hi> if he have them not <hi>from vs</hi> (againe) in <hi>duty,</hi> it had beene better for vs we had <hi>never beene borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lay theſe holy conſiderations to hart, &amp; offer not to preſume vpon grace in <hi>thine owne time,</hi> it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſin to doe ſoe: that man is extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>graceleſſe,</hi> that dare's preſume of <hi>grace</hi> in <hi>extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> time. <hi>They</hi> that come to crave more then <hi>common kindnes</hi> of vs, muſt be more then <hi>common freinds</hi> vnto vs; litle reaſon hath God to be more then <hi>vſually good</hi> to them, who have beene <hi>groſſly evill</hi> to him; as all <hi>they</hi> are who render him not his right in their <hi>first dayes.</hi> If we would be the Lords <hi>for ever,</hi> let vs <hi>ever</hi> reſolve to be ſoe <hi>at</hi> the <hi>firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dearely beloved, take theſe things into <hi>deliberatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> let them <hi>lodge</hi> in our harts, <hi>rest,</hi> and <hi>rooste</hi> in our myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that ſoe the Lord our God may take vs into his favour and compaſſion. <hi>Olde, yonge, middle-age, all ages,</hi> have this in good <hi>remembrance,</hi> for it is a truth that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20805:40"/>make's vs <hi>happy</hi> if we hearken to it, <hi>miſerable</hi> if we doe not. To the <hi>aged</hi> I ſay (yet not I, but the Lord) looke <hi>backward,</hi> ſee how much of your <hi>glaſſe</hi> is out, and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> how litle remayneth to <hi>run,</hi> and <hi>run</hi> apace to the living God to be received, before <hi>all</hi> be <hi>gone,</hi> and no hope be left; thinke that voyce of God ſpoken to you:
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>[It is ſufficient that we have ſpent the time past after the lusts of the flesh &amp;c]</hi> &amp; therevpon haſten to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven with all expedition, it may (be the Lord may take that <hi>litle</hi> time that is left, and receiue you into everlaſting habitations. To the <hi>younge</hi> I ſay alſo, [<hi>Remember thy Creator</hi> (&amp; thy <hi>redeemer</hi> too) <hi>in the dayes of thy youth</hi>] and jmagine that other voyce of heaven ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you [<hi>for it is now time to a wake;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 13.11</note> &amp;c] it is great reaſon that the <hi>flowre</hi> of your abilityes should be the Lords, <hi>from whome</hi> you had them, and <hi>to whome</hi> your account muſt be made for them.</p>
            <p>In a <hi>word,</hi> I ſay to you <hi>all,</hi> and to <hi>every one</hi> of you: Doe but thinke 1. how <hi>farre</hi> it is to heaven, ſeing we muſt goe from <hi>ſin</hi> to <hi>grace,</hi> that we may goe <hi>thence,</hi> to <hi>glory</hi> 2. how <hi>hard</hi> it is, to finde the way, becauſe flesh &amp; blood ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not <hi>shew</hi> it: <hi>then</hi> 3 how <hi>hard</hi> to enter, &amp; goe on, becauſe the gate is ſo <hi>straight,</hi> &amp; the enemy ſoe <hi>strong,</hi> &amp; we ſoe <hi>weake,</hi> &amp; <hi>wearied out</hi> with ſin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually clogging vs. And ſoe I end with that ſpeech in Iob: [<hi>If thou wilt ſeeke vnto God</hi> early,
<note place="margin">Job. 8.3.6.7;</note> 
               <hi>and make thy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> to <hi>the almighty: if thou be</hi> pure <hi>and</hi> vpright, <hi>ſurely he would</hi> now awake <hi>vnto thee, and make the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of thy</hi> righteouſnes <hi>proſperous: and though thy</hi> begining <hi>be but</hi> ſmall, <hi>yet thy</hi> latter end <hi>should greatly</hi> encreaſe.] And that <hi>thus</hi> we may be, and <hi>thus</hi> doe, Let <hi>all ſorts</hi> vnceſſantly ſeeke his face for ever.</p>
            <closer>Glory be to God on high.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
